<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The nevv Gospel, not the true Gospel. Or, A discovery of the life and death, doctrin, and doings of Mr. Iohn Traske, and the effects of all, in his followers Wherein a mysterie of iniquity is briefly disclosed, a seducer unmasked, and all warned to beware of imposters. As also a confutation of the uncomfortable error, of Mr. Boye, concerning the plague, out of Psal. 91. By Edvv. Norice.</title>
            <author>Norris, Edward, 1584-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08318</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18645</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113242</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848479</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848479</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13575</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08318)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13575)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1212:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The nevv Gospel, not the true Gospel. Or, A discovery of the life and death, doctrin, and doings of Mr. Iohn Traske, and the effects of all, in his followers Wherein a mysterie of iniquity is briefly disclosed, a seducer unmasked, and all warned to beware of imposters. As also a confutation of the uncomfortable error, of Mr. Boye, concerning the plague, out of Psal. 91. By Edvv. Norice.</title>
                  <author>Norris, Edward, 1584-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 55, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Bishop, for Henry Hood, and are to be sold at his shop in St. Dunstans Church-yard in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Traske, John.  The true gospel vindicated, from the reproach of a new gospel.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Traske, John, d. ca. 1638. --  True gospel vindicated, from the reproach of a new gospel --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Boye, Rice --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13575:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13575:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NEVV GOSPEL, NOT THE TRVE GOSPEL OR, A diſcovery of the Life and Death, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin, and Doings of Mr. <hi>Iohn Traske,</hi> and the effects of all, in his Followers.</p>
            <p>Wherein a myſterie of iniquity is briefly diſcloſed, a Seducer unmarked, and all war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to beware of Impoſtors.</p>
            <p>As alſo a Confutation of the uncomfortable error, of Mr. <hi>Boye,</hi> concerning the Plague, out of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 24.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Many falſe prophets ſhall riſe, and ſhall deceive many.</p>
            </q>
            <p>By EDVV. NORICE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Biſhop,</hi> for <hi>Henry Hood,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church-yard in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1638.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13575:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13575:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE NEW GOSPEL, NOT THE TRVE GOSPEL.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it was the care of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt the great Shepheard of the Flock, to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warne the ſame in generall of all Wolves, and falſe prophets, that ſhould ariſe (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the later times) and deceive ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: ſo is it a ſubordinate duty and no leſſe needfull, when ſuch falſe prophets do ariſe in thoſe times, being eſpied, to give particular notice of them, and to point (as it were) with the finger unto them, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did of ſome ſuch like,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.15.</note> 
               <hi>This is hee, beware of him.</hi> The conſideration whereof, hath moved, and thus farre enboldned me to tender unto publike view (with ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto allowance) this briefe diſcovery (as but the point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the finger) of ſuch a ſeducing Impoſtor, and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Deceiver in our owne times; I meane Mr. <hi>John Traske:</hi> A man well knowne by common fame, and yet not knowne according to his manifold deceits but of a few, turning and winding himſelfe like another <hi>Proteus,</hi> into ſo many formes as that he could not eaſily be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be the ſame individuall, but deſcryed only by his unconſtancy to be none other, becauſe therein he had not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13575:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>his like: this man falling from one errour to another, and purſuing all with equall vehemency, at length fell upon a<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.9.</note> new way of Evangelizing; underſtanding the Goſpell, the Kingdome of Chriſt, the ſtate of Grace, the nature of Faith, as things utterly abſtracted from all Law, habits of Grace, ſignes of Faith, and ſanctification it ſelfe: ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up a conceited new Creature entire of himſelf, as free from ſinne as Ieſus Chriſt, to whom nothing belongeth but joy, tranquillity, and triumph; nor to that perſon in whom this new Creature is formed: no, not though hee fell into the fouleſt ſinnes, and perpetrated the groſſeſt impieties, as murthers, or adulteries, or ſuch like, becauſe theſe were but acted by the fleſh, and not at all by the new Creature in him:<note place="margin">Familiſme.</note> therfore is he never to mourne or grieve for any ſuch thing, but ever to rejoyce, knowing that in this eſtate no ſinne ſhall hurt him, neither is he to queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the favour of God, whatſoever hee doth; that being farre worſe than the ſinne he committeth, but ever to bee confident. Into which joyfull condition all are brought only by beleeving, which faith is not to be tryed by any ſignes, fruits, or effects, but only by the perſwaſion it ſelfe: and all this effected, not by any uſe of the Law in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but only the Goſpell and promiſes, applying the ſame to all that ſo do beleeve, yet not as faith is a condition of the Covenant, or an inſtrument of Iuſtification lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hold on Chriſt, but only as a qualification in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>Whereupon all ſuch Preachers as made any uſe of the Law in their teaching, or gave any ſignes for tryall of faith or grace; motives or meanes to duties, rules of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, or ſuch like, were preſently rejected as Legaliſts, Iuſtitiaries, meſſengers of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſilly naturaliſts that underſtand not the myſterie of the Goſpell,<note n="*" place="margin">They are his own words, pag. 28.</note> yea Iewes, and worſe than Iewes, their congregations not true, but pretended Chriſtian aſſemblies: thereupon alſo his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers ſequeſtring themſelves to ſuch as were their owne way, with a high diſdaine of all others, gave themſelves to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13575:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>mirth and jollity, ſuch triumphing and glorying, laughter and glee,<note place="margin">Iudges 12.6.</note> as if it were the only <hi>Shibboleth</hi> whereby to bee diſcerned from the miſerable Legaliſts that held mourning and ſorrow for ſinne, care of dutyes towards God, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour for ſanctification by his Spirit in themſelves; ſome of them proceeding ſo farre, as diſdainfully to aske,<note place="margin">R. O. A forge of fancies.</note> what that ſanctification was, we talked ſo much of, for hee knew not what it meaned; (which we may eaſily beleeve) yea and to demand whether God will not accept of our prayers without the mediation of his Sonne: and ſome of them in the mean time falling into ingemniated adulteries, to the great ſcandall of the truth (they ſeemed to profeſſe) yet not ſhewing the leaſt remorſe for the ſame themſelves, nor others in their behalfe, but with this come-off in a merry manner, that, if a man be in Chriſt, no ſinne ſhall hurt him. I ſhame to relate theſe things, but know them to be true.</p>
            <p>Now theſe are the effects of this mans doctrin, and of his new deviſed Goſpell, but the way and courſe hee took in venting the ſame, was this: firſt hee would in publike,<note place="margin">The methode of a Seducer.</note> (whereſoever hee was admitted to preach) deliver ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry truths in a plaine way, but with extraordinary ſhew of zeale and affection, thus to gaine him credit, and a good eſteeme of all; then, if any were taken with him, he would in private proceed further, and doctrinate them in his my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries; if they conſented, they were his owne; if not, then would he deny what he had ſaid, and beare them downe with ſcoffs and deriſion; which courſe he alſo took in his conferences, and diſputes, denying, and ſhifting any thing he had ſpoken, or defended, when it came to any publike diſlike; by which meanes none or very few that dealt with him, Miniſters or others could eſcape reproach, ſo far as the credit of his tongue extended, or yet of his followers, who therein have ſhewed themſelves (many of them) <hi>tam moribus ſimiles, quàm voce, magiſtro,</hi> like their maſter; in a ſhameleſſe, and unreaſonable manner; a taſte wherof both he, and they not long ſince yeelded: when, at a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13575:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>having vented many foule and erroncous points, and afterwards being taxed therewith, they utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied that any ſuch things (though many) were ſpoken in their hearings,<note place="margin">O this very practiſe Maſter Doctor <hi>Taylor</hi> complaines in his <hi>Regula vitae,</hi> pag. 63.</note> which he ſithence hath yet acknowledged in print; but with ſuch conſtructions and new deviſed interpretations, as were never thought on, nor imagined there, yea directly againſt his expreſſe Aſſertions in other places, turning ſome of them into ridles, and ambiguous enunciations, like <hi>Apollo's</hi> Oracles, to make an evaſion, as hereafter (God willing) ſhall be diſcovered.</p>
            <p>And becauſe in his late<note n="*" place="margin">Publiſhed ſince his death (as its ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted) by Mr. <hi>Boye.</hi>
               </note> printed pamphlet, he hath not only blended the truth, with his cunning head, but alſo blaſted the names of all that oppoſe him with reproach: (eſpecially my ſelfe for that ſmall diſcovery I made of him) I think fit to forewarne the Reader concerning the ſame; (being perſonall matters) firſt, that his whole E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the Reader, (being wholly defamatory) is ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly falſe, and compoſed of meere fictions of his owne braine, not only without any evidence, but againſt the teſtimony and certain<note n="*" place="margin">Yea of Mr. <hi>Boye</hi> himſelfe his brother in evill.</note> knowledge of thouſands; decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring therein his brazen forehead, and raging ſpirit to vent any thing (bee it never ſo untrue) to ſerve the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent turne, which (were it fit to mention the particulars) might in few words eaſily be diſcovered, the accuſations being notoriouſly falſe either of them: next, for his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Apologie, wherein he utterly denies that hee was ever cenſured in the Starre-Chamber for Iudaiſme or any matters of that kind; it is as impudently falſe, as the reſt: for beſides a printed ſpeech now extant of that lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Biſhop <hi>Andrewes</hi> made at his cenſure in the Starre-Chamber, the very Records of that Honourable Court concurring; doe both abundantly teſtifie, one of the principall cauſes of his cenſure there to be for Iudaizing in matters of dayes and meates; for which, (beſides other caſtigations) hee was<note n="*" place="margin">Mentioned alſo by Dr. <hi>Sclater</hi> in his confutation of him about that time.</note> ſtigmatized with the letter I, in the forehead for a lew which he bare to his laſt: ſo that, it is marveilous the man ſhould or could bee ſo ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13575:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>as utterly to deny (and that in print) that hee was ever at all cenſured in that Court for Iudaiſme or any ſuch errors; unleſſe the Lord did ſo farre leave him to himſelfe, to diſcover thereby his impudency, that in his other Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and proteſtations, he might not be truſted; for who that's wiſe, will beleeve or truſt ſuch a one, as hath a heart and a forehead,<note n="*" place="margin">Conſultò, &amp; cogitatò.</note> deliberatly to deny that <hi>(in terminis)</hi> that he well knew himſelfe to be knowne in all the land, and to be recorded againſt him? Wiſhing therefore thoſe that have beene the favourers, and furtherers of this man and his doctrin all this while, now to open their eyes, and behold the deceitfulneſſe of the one,<note place="margin">Their own conſciences can tell them who they are.</note> and the danger of the other (being both ſo manifeſt) and in ſtead of their inſolent, and unworthy cenſures of others, to ſmite upon the thigh, and judge themſelves for their ſinfull levity and partiality, in departing ſo ſoone from the truth they had formerly embraced, and entertaining ſo ſuddenly an erroneous man branded in the Church of God, for a phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtick, and great abuſer of the holy Scriptures; alſo for bezelling, ſhifting, and concealing the things they heard him maintaine with their eares, and know in their owne hearts to bee truly objected againſt him; being ſuch a way, as no good cauſe needed, neither will a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ever uſe.</p>
            <p>And becauſe our Lord referres us much, to the fruits, for the diſcerning of falſe prophets, upon the mention of the former, I think fit to adde further concerning his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.16.</note> what I have heard from the teſtimony of divers perſons of worth and credit: that as his doctrines, and opinions tend all to liberty, ſo his practiſe ſavoured ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the ſame, not Chriſtian liberty allowed to all, but carnall licentiouſneſſe condemned in all that profeſſe the Goſpell of Chriſt, even the ſame mentioned by St. <hi>Jude, when the grace of God is turned</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>into laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viouſneſſe, verſ.</hi> 4. for ſo it ſeemed to be with this man, who in his ordinary converſation as he profeſſed nothing but mirth and jollity; ſo in his private carriage was he as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13575:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>frollike, eſpecially with that ſexe, in which hee moſt delighted, towards whom hee uſed ſuch familiarity, with his embracings and<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Agreeable to <hi>Ovids</hi> ſilthy inſtructions, and the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of <hi>H. N.</hi>
               </note> tongue fornications, with ſuch other proffers, as they that were modeſt, utterly ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred his private ſociety, and complained thereof ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to their friends as very foule and ſhamefull; and how farre any of them, with whom he was moſt converſant, ſhared in theſe things, themſelves can beſt tell: but what may not ſuch be drawne unto, as denie any feare of God, in regard of his power, and juſtice: that diſclaime the Law of God, to be any rule of their lives: that allow no mourning for the fouleſt ſinnes: that reſt upon a bare per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion for all their evidence of faith or grace: that make mirth and joy, the ſubſtance of their religion: that boaſt how no ſinne can hurt them, being in Chriſt: I ſay what may not ſuch doe, when occaſion is offered? fleſh and blood will act their parts, and when the underſtanding is ſo corrupt, how can the affections be pure? the ſame being wanting to ſeaſon the one, that ſhould informe the other.</p>
            <p>But to leave them, and returne againe to their leader, beſides his other evill properties, how mutable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant he was in his doings all his life long, I think not amiſſe (in part) to diſcover by the recitall of a certain let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter written ſince the bruite of his death, by an honeſt Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen of London to his friend in the Countrey, and it is thus:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>A Letter.</head>
                  <p>MY love remembred, hoping of your health and welfare in the Lord. T. A. meeting with me, asked mee, if I had ſeene a book of Mr. <hi>Traskes</hi> newly printed, and withall deſired me to help you to one, and to write you two or three lines; which accordingly I have done. Touching the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor Mr. <hi>Traske,</hi> were it not to forewarn others to take heed of by-pathes which lead to ſchiſme, and herefie, I ſhould nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther write, nor ſpeak of him a word, for that the man is dead, and gone to give account to the higheſt Judge. Yet in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13575:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>that (though hee be dead) his workes ſtill teach, and ſpeake hereſies and blaſphemies; they may ſafely all, both bee ſpoken and written againſt. As for Mr. <hi>Traske,</hi> I have well knowne the man theſe full twenty yeeres; at firſt hee was a Schoolemaſter (no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity man, only a <hi>Latine</hi> Scholler) but afterwards being caſt into priſons for opinions, he learned and ſtudied the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek,</hi> and got a ſmattering therof, that by <hi>Indexes</hi> he could do ſome little matter; but for zeale it was alwayes in him heady, and violent, that in which way he took, he marched like <hi>Iehu</hi> moſt furiouſly, making di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions in the Church about <hi>London,</hi> and drawing in one Mr. <hi>Gr.</hi> with him, to maintaine foure points differing from other Divines; as namely,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>— 1. That none but ſuch as were converted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, could convert others.</item>
                     <item>— 2. That one child of God might know anothers election, as certainly as his own.</item>
                     <item>— 3. That Repentance was not only begun, but alſo finiſhed, before juſtifying faith.</item>
                     <item>— 4. That none that were juſtifyed did commit ſinne.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Having continued teaching theſe Doctrines a while, hee had very many followers, upon whom he obtruded the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Lords day, after a Iudaicall manner, neither to kindle fires nor to dreſſe meates: the which manner of obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation was to him and others an introduction to the obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the very Judaicall Sabbath; and was an occaſion of ſtumbling to five or ſixe of his followers to deny our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, to be the true Meſſiah: one of which Mr. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Gouge</hi> helped to reduce unto the truth. This Mr. <hi>Traske</hi> while he held thoſe former opinions (of which ſome made ſuch deſperate Collections) was ſo high blowne with erroneous zeale, that hee thought, he might bee a ſecond <hi>Elias</hi> ſent to diſcover Antichriſt, and to turn the hearts of the Fathers to the Children; he thought alſo, that he could do miracles, and to that end he ſent to King <hi>Iames</hi> to have acceſſe unto him,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13575:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>to cure him of his Gout; alſo hee layed hands in an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall manner upon foure men, ſending them forth to preach, foraſmuch as Antichriſtianiſme is, as hatefull to God, as Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſme; therefore it is no leſſe needfull, that men be extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily ſent out to overthrow the one, aſwell as the other: three of which Apoſtolicall men are dead, the fourth is yet alive, but hath renounced thoſe fooleries. Then after ſome long impriſonment, his zeale was ſo cooled, that hee revoked all, and recanting was ſet at liberty, and not authorized, but only permitted to preach, which he not long continuing in, fell to familiſticall points, divers of which, are inſerted in this book, though he turne and winde them to qualifie them, for the dazeling of his unknowne Reader, yet the points are truly-the Familiſts, and the undeniable conſequences of their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. Now after ſome progreſſe in this more worſe than hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theniſh Divinity, Mr. <hi>Traske</hi> had at laſt turned himſelfe to the Iacobites, or ſemi-ſeparatiſts in one of whoſe houſes he dyed (at leaſt the mans wife being that way) from whoſe houſe ſome of that ſocietie carried him to his grave in <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> Church-yard, where they caſt him in, with the heeles that way that the heads of other men lie, contrary to all men, and leaſt the Miniſter ſhould come to bury him, according to the order, they ranne all away, and there left him to bee covered by others; ſome beholding their carriages thought them to be drunk, which J think alſo, yet not with wine but with ſpirituall giddineſſe; from which, wee have all cauſe to pray that wee may bee delivered. So I commit you to the tuition of our good God, who is able to keepe us blameleſſe, till his bleſſed appearance. Amen. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <date>December <hi>27th. 1636.</hi>
                     </date>
                     <signed>Yours to be commanded, <hi>T. S.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>What is it to be an <hi>ignis fatuus</hi> in the Church, and to be carryed about, with every wind of doctrine, if this be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13575:6"/>not? what more certaine evidence can there be of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable ſpirit, yea of a man drunk with pride and arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, than thus to reele to and fro, from one extreamity to another, and never to ſettle in the way of truth? yet there is much more of his falſehood and fraud, diſcovered in the treatiſe enſuing; which I therefore lay open, not to trample on the dead, or to defame an enemy, (both which are equally offenſive) but to warne and informe the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, aſwell enemies, as friends, of the danger of a Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer; who under the vizour, and maske of truth and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, hath vented pernitious errors, tending to much looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and prophaneneſſe, leaving the ſame as his Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to the Church, and the only doctrine to bee received, which alſo, too many admire and follow. That Apology, therefore, which was once made in the ſame caſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the like perſons by a learned Doctor,<note place="margin">Doctor <hi>Sclater</hi> on 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.4. <hi>pag.</hi> 15.</note> I would make bold to uſe in defence of my ſelfe herein, againſt his preſent admirers, might it not ſeeme too ſharp a paſſage. <hi>Even, becauſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>his ſpeech frets like a gangrene,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and increaſeth to more ungodlineſſe in that giddy multitude, whoſe ſtile it will ever be, to be conſtant in</hi> levitate ſuâ. <hi>Such whir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligigge, weather-cock braines there are amongſt them, ſo chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh in underſtanding, that they are whirried about, with every blaſt of doctrine, &amp;c.</hi> a ſmart laſh,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.13.</note> and yet (it ſeemes too well deſerved of many, who in ſuch caſes ought to bee ſharply reproved, that they may be ſound in the faith; eſpecially ſeeing that they all take ſuch liberty themſelves; not ſo much to reproove, confute, or diſlike, ſuch as diſſent from them; as to revile, ſlander,<note place="margin">The very man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Browne,</hi> and <hi>Boye.</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.18.</note> and defame their perſons and opinions with opprobrious termes, ſcoffs, and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy imputations; a lively monument wherof he hath left at his death (like an <hi>Abſoloms</hi> pillar) wherein there is gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven neither truth, honeſty, nor modeſty;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Trasks</hi> Goſpel.</note> yet admired by many of them as a ſingular work; (O the power of theſe ſpirituall illuſions,) for the refuting whereof I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed ſome paines in ſearching out the quinteſſenſe of his myſterie, to prevent any further proceeding of the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13575:7"/>wherein if the Reader obſerve a ſharper kind of lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, than may be thought expedient, let him conſider it is in defence of the very Goſpell of Chriſt, the ſtate of Grace, the nature of Faith, the way of Salvation; no ſmall matters; againſt a cunning Seducer, many ſelfe-willed, and ſelfe-conceited followers, to whom eaſie and ſoft handling is contemptible, whom a ſtill and low voice will not awaken, unleſſe a man cry in their eares, and<note n="*" place="margin">Iude <hi>23.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> pluck them as brands out of the fire: yet is there nothing but what is regulated by the truth, and within the bounds of modeſty; craving leave alſo for this boldneſſe, in mine owne behalfe, inaſmuch as they have bent their ſpeciall forces againſt me, and that more of their myſteries are come to my knowledge than may to many others, (though better able to deale in this kind) who alſo may not have that vacancy from other imployments as (unwillingly) I have at this time, (yet ſubmitting all to approbation, and allowance;) wherefore hoping of a charitable conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all, of that which is intended for the good of all; and that it ſhall be no juſt offence to any, that among ſo many in the Church<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19.</note> there is one Seducer diſcovered: I give this encouragement to the Reader; that he is like no more to be troubled with <hi>Traske,</hi> and his matters, this being the laff Act of the Scene, and the man diſveſted, hoping that all his errors ſhall die with him, and that the true Goſpell of Chriſt withall the branches thereof ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper and flouriſh, with abundance of pretious fruits for ever.</p>
            <p>Although it be moſt true which the holy Scriptures te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie, that there is but one Lord,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 45. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.8.</note> one Faith, one Baptiſme, one true Goſpell, containing the ancient covenant of grace in Chriſt, who is yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame for ever, in himſelfe, and to his people: yet ſuch hath beene the audacious cunning of Satan, and his inſtruments as to transforme themſelves into Angells of light, and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of righteouſneſſe, to the end, that they may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vent, and ſet abroach another doctrine reſembling the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13575:7"/>true, and another Goſpell very like (but not the ſame) to that we have received, thereby to beguile and enſnare the ſimple; which kind of deceitfull workers, as the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle diſcryed in his time, and complained of them,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13, 14.</note> ſo have we the like cauſe in ours, wherein ariſe ſome Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Seducers of like condition. Among which, this Mr. <hi>Iohn Traske,</hi> may ſtand for a principall, who in this time of light, hath taken upon him to dictate, and ſend abroad his Goſpell grounds (as he calls them) into all parts, pretending that they containe in them a more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect diſcovery of the Goſpell of Chriſt than ever was made before; and a more glorious way of walking by, than any have found till he diſcried it. Wherein nevertheleſſe, are couched, and hidden many very pernitious errors contrary to the truth of the Goſpell of Chriſt, &amp; that in points fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall, and of the higheſt conſequence.<note n="*" place="margin">An advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Traſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſme.</note> A ſhort diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery whereof being formerly publiſhed, as an Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix to another work, and the ſame ſtiled (as it deſerved) a new Goſpell: hee hath ſince laboured to vindicate his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin from that<note n="*" place="margin">In his late printed book.</note> reproach, calling it the true Goſpell, and no new Goſpell; to which end hee hath ſhuffled up the Scriptures with falſe ſenſes: put many faire colours upon ſome of the points, and utterly falſifyed the reſt with his explanations, thereby to deceive the ſimple and credulous: for the unmasking of which<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13.</note> Iugler with his juglings (being in matters of ſo high a nature) I have here diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the truth of his Aſſertions, as hee hath maintained them, not alone by writing, but by word of mouth, in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne diſputation, and conference had about the ſame, and that not his Goſpell grounds alone, but in other formes, delivered under his own hand, that the very quint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſence of his errors may be knowne.</p>
            <p>But before I come to the particulars, I think it not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to lay before the eyes of the Reader theſe deceits of his in generall; the better to diſcerne and judge of his carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age in the particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whereas he pretendeth, and ſolemnly proteſteth in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13575:8"/>the name of the Higheſt, that he maintaineth none other Doctrin,<note place="margin">This is at large in a Letter.</note> than the ſame, that is taught by all our Divines, preached in Pulpits, and defended by writings, &amp;c. yet he hath not, nor doth alleadge in any place, any one Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor for the confirmation of what he holds, but more than ſo, diſclaimes all our teaching as Iewiſh; our Miniſters as Legaliſts and Meſſengers of <hi>Moſes;</hi> our congregations, as but pretended Chriſtian Aſſemblies: ſending out his dictates under the name of Goſpell grounds; his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers alſo profeſſing, that they never heard the Goſpell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for if the former be true, how can the later ſtand.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he, all along, caſteth upon me the reproach of a Slanderer, with other foule invectives, for charging him with ſuch opinions; and yet acknowledgeth many of them, in particular to be glorious truths, which he own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and defendeth; as if I had ſlandered him, with a matter of truth, and done him wrong in publiſhing his glorious myſteries, ſo eager and virulent was his ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That under the pretence of explaining the Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he changeth the very ſenſe of them as they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by himſelfe; and runnes along with a falſe ſenſe never intended; only to caſt miſts before the eyes of the Reader, that his errors may not be perceived; like unto a certaine fiſh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarchs</hi> moralls:</note> whoſe property it is, to ſtaine the water with a black ſtuffe, like inke, to blind the eyes of the Fiſhers. His explanations therefore, I take properly to be derived, <hi>ex Plano,</hi> from a deceiver, or jugler, that can caſt miſts, and in ſtead of them, will ſubſtitute and annexe the true and genuine explication of the Aſſertions, as he indeed held, and hath elſewhere defended them, inſiſting ſpecially upon the diſcovery of them, the confutation following of it ſelfe, the errors being ſo foule.</p>
            <p>To come then to a ſcanning of the particulars, and herein to follow, not his confuſed order, (done of purpoſe to diſturb the Reader) but the ſame they were firſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in the Advertiſment, they are theſe following.</p>
            <div n="1" type="assertion">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:13575:8"/>
               <head>1. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> The Law is a Rule of the fleſh, and to walk after the Law, is to walk after the fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.12.</head>
               <head type="sub">Explication.</head>
               <p>HIs meaning is, that the very morall Law of God, is a carnall rule, to live by; according to his common invectives againſt the ſame, in ſtiling it, an earthly, and a carnall commandment: as alſo, his application of thoſe words of the Apoſtle, to the morall Law, <hi>that walk not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit, Rom.</hi> 8.1. that is, in his conſtruction, not after the Law, but after the Goſpell, wherein he calls the Law a rule of the fleſh, and perverteth the Scripture to maintaine it; for if that be ſo to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, then, by the Law of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.25.</note> in the former verſe (on which this depends) muſt be meant, the Goſpell, and by the law of ſinne the morall Law; ſo that, the law of the members, the law of ſinne, and the morall Law, are all one in his ſenſe; and then muſt the very Law it ſelfe be ſinne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and a Commander of unrighteous things;<note place="margin">The height of Antinomiſme.</note> an enemy to holineſſe; an oppoſite to the work of the ſpirit; and utterly repugnant to the Goſpell (even as it is a rule of obedience,) then muſt it alſo bee diſclaimed, abandoned, and renounced, as evill and impure, with all the contents of it, and not in any ſenſe to be taught in the Church; than which, what can be more blaſphemouſly, and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly ſpoken? or how can the <hi>Turkiſh Alcoran</hi> it ſelfe bee harder cenſured? which is the more unexcuſable in this Seducer, in that the holy Apoſtle was ſo carefull in thoſe very places to prevent ſuch a conſtruction of his words; firſt, demanding whether the Law where ſin? which he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13575:9"/>anſwereth with deteſtation,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.7.12.12.14.22. <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>God forbid;</hi> then, plainly affirming the Law to be holy, and juſt, and good: a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall doctrine, wherein he delighted as a ſpirituall man; whereunto the carnall mind, could not be ſubject becauſe it is carnall: caſting all the blame, not on the Law, but on the fleſh, for any hurt, or evill we have by it, as not cauſed by the Law, but occaſioned by our owne corruption, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides many other places to that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Now in the explanation,<note place="margin">I referre my ſelfe to his book for what I cite all along.</note> the Seducer would declare his meaning to be againſt thoſe only, that ſought life, and righteouſneſſe, by the works of the Law; that to ſuch it is a rule of the fleſh, pretending that he was oppoſed by ſome of that way; and thereupon layed downe his dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions againſt it: but why doth hee not name who they were, that did ſo? or why doth he not handle the point, as other godly men have done? but thus break out againſt the Law it ſelfe, calling it a rule of the fleſh, to make it vile: but all this is nothing elſe than meere deceit and colluſion; pretending a cauſe that never was, in any of them, at whom he aimeth, no, not to a thought: upon which falſe ſuppoſition alſo, it is, that he reproacheth all other Miniſters that make any uſe of the Law, for Legaliſts and Iuſtitiaries, as if they taught righteouſneſſe by works, becauſe they make the Law a rule of obedience; which is common and (I doubt) wilfull calumny, of all his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, who know well enough, how farre they are from ſuch doctrines, and drifts, whom they diſclaime, and decline.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="assertion">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:13575:9"/>
               <head>2. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> The Law is not to be preached, to belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, by Goſpell Miniſters.</head>
               <head type="sub">Explication.</head>
               <p>HIs meaning is, that the Law is not to be preached at all in the Church of God, neither to beleevers, nor unbeleevers, either for repentance or obedience: and that, his meaning is ſo, his words declare, which are theſe; <hi>And why may it not be affirmed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In his confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</note> 
                  <hi>that ſeeing there is no Commiſſion to preach the Law at all, now under the Goſpell: and ſeeing the Goſpell containes the whole mind and will of God; and that the Apoſtles did never preach the Law at all: (but as ſubordinate to the Goſpell) and doth enjoyne</hi> Timothy <hi>to charge ſome, that they teach no other Doctrine but the faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A clauſe added againſt the reſt.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. why may we not ſay, that the Goſpell only is to bee prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to all, aſwell as to beleevers? except any can ſhew a larger Commiſſion than Chriſt himſelfe, &amp;c. pag.</hi> 50. Theſe words are plaine enough; <hi>There is no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to preach the Law [at all] the Gospell is [only] to bee preached to all:</hi> Generall and peremptory aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, without exception; yet nevertheleſſe to hide his flat Antinomiſme, in his explanation he tells us that the Law, as law is not to be preached to beleevers; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards demands; <hi>Who ever denyed the Lawes uſe or excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to diſcover ſinne; convict ſuch as the Goſpell ſhines not unto; to be a ground for all humane Lawes; the very rule of love; a meanes to ſhew the greatneſſe of ſinne; of very plentifull uſe to beleevers, &amp;c.</hi> One would think that the ſame man, could not own, both theſe aſſertions at once, and ſet them down both in the ſame Chapter. What? hath the Law ſo many excellentuſes, to beleevers, and unbeleevers and yet is there no Commiſſion at all, to preach it? doth it containe ſo many excellent truths, and of that neceſſity in the Church; and yet is it no part of the mind and will of God, to bee
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13575:10"/>revealed unto men?<note place="margin">Doctor <hi>Taylor</hi> his <hi>Regula vitae,</hi> is very uſefull for all theſe points.</note> how to make all this accord in any good conſtruction, I acknowledge to be paſt my skill, or (I ſuppoſe) any mans elſe; for take it according to his firſt words: the Law, as Law is not to bee preached, but as ſubordinate to the Goſpell; yet then it muſt be preached howſoever, and is within the Commiſſion of a Goſpell Miniſter, which before he denyed: either the Seducer wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wit to ſee his own contradictions, or elſe he was very wicked to ſpeak againſt the truth, and his own conſcience together: the later is moſt to be ſuſpected; but then, they are men to be admired that will ſee neither of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="assertion">
               <head>3. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> If repentance and faith bee wrought only by the Goſpell: then what doth the Law work in any mans converſion to God, or conformity to Chriſt.</head>
               <head type="sub">Explication.</head>
               <p>THis demand, hee acknowledgeth, to be truly inferr'd by him, upon the premiſſes of one of his (then) diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, according to the doctrin he had firſt taught him: and yet, leſt he ſhould loſe his habit of rayling, hee keeps the word<note n="*" place="margin">This is his, <hi>Keax.</hi>
                  </note> Slanderer on foot ſtill, although it be the truth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his own hand. Concerning which point, I will ſay no more; but if the Law ſerve to diſcover ſinne, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince men (as before he hath acknowledged) and that this diſcovery, and convincing bee neceſſary to bring men to repentance, (ſeeing they cannot repent of what they know not) how then is the Law wholly excluded from having any hand in the ſame at all? was it not that, and matter of that kind, which S. <hi>Peter</hi> uſed to convince the Iewes withall, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. and is it not that which diſcovers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all men, their own unrighteouſneſſe and miſery, that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13575:10"/>they may ſeek unto Chriſt for righteouſneſſe and mercy, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19. doth not that regulate our love, and ſo our conformity to Chriſt, and his requirings, <hi>John</hi> 13.34. but theſe matters of repentance, humiliation for ſin, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorrow, ſanctification of ſpirit, feare of God, care of obedience, and ſuch like, are all in too low a ſphere, for his ſublimity, and not in the compaſſe of his mounted ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; only faith, and joy, are the matters he is converſant in: the other ſerve for poore Legaliſts to feed upon, that know no better; but it followes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="assertion">
               <head>4. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> The law did once diſcover ſin, it doth ſo no more; nor yet for direction: love herein tranſcends the law, as far as life, doth death.</head>
               <head type="sub">Explication.</head>
               <p>HIs meaning is, that now in time of the Goſpell, the Law doth neither ſerve to diſcover ſin, nor yet to be a rule of obedience; for it was alleadged by him, in way of Anſwer, to that of the Apoſtle: <hi>By the law is the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of finne, Rom.</hi> 3.20. and Chap. 7. 7. to which, he replyed that though it did ſo heretofore, yet it doth not ſo now, thoſe times, and that uſe of the Law, are paſt and gone, and ſo out of date; the Goſpell now doth all without the Law, which is his ſpirituall ſenſe and the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of his way, but to colour the matter (being foule in appearance) hee tells us in his explanation, that the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſt doth better ſet forth the odiouſneſſe of ſinne, than the terrors of the Law: which is no part of the point what doth moſt ſet out the odiouſneſſe of ſinne,<note place="margin">Ignoratio ele nchis</note> but what doth diſcover the ſinnes themſelves, in their kinds, and ſeverall branches: which muſt needs be the Law according to the Apoſtles teſtimony; the very definition of ſin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13575:11"/>[<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] the tranſgreſſion of the Law, 1. <hi>John</hi> 3.4. then is it to be preached with the Goſpell, for repentance.</p>
               <p>Concerning the other branch, about the directing uſe of the Law; to juſtifie his deny all, he gives us to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand (as if none knew it before) that the inward princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from which all true obedience proceeds, is love; which inward grace doth farre tranſcend the letter without, as if that were the queſtion, from what inward principle true obedience proceeded? and not rather, by what Rule the ſame is regulated and ordered, which is the Law of God, diſcovering good and evill. But his practiſe in this is, as if a man rejecting all directions for his way in a journey; ſhould give this for his reaſon, that the principle of motion muſt be in himſelfe,<note place="margin">Charitas conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net in ſeſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletionem om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium Dei man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datorum. Ameſ. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> medull.</note> and not in ſuch outward directions: ſo doth this man; but therein it is marvellous what a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence he makes betweene love and the law, as if they were two contraries, or (at leaſt) not of the ſame kind: when the Scriptures acknowledge them to be but one, and the ſame: love being the very ſumme and ſubſtance of the whole Law, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.40. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.14.</p>
               <p>But there is yet a more dangerous and ſuſpitious paſſage following, where he ſtands to maintaine, that love hath no rules, becauſe God is love, who being infinite, is not to be limited by any law: as if there were no odds, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Deity it ſelfe, and a created quality in the hearts of men, of which wee ſpeak: which Aſſertion of his therefore ſavours ſtrongly of Familiſme, who blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly ſay,<note place="margin">H N. <hi>In his</hi> Evangelium Regni.</note> that God is manned, and man is Godded, with ſuch like, making no difference betweene the eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all attributes of the Almighty, and the workes and effects, of his Spirit in men; ſo this man will admit no rules for love in us, becauſe God is unlimitted; but to proceed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="assertion">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:13575:11"/>
               <head>5. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> The new covenant hath no condition at all: faith is not the condition of the Goſpels promiſes; but only a qualification in us.</head>
               <head type="sub">Explication.</head>
               <p>TO all this, he ſaith nothing, but that the condition required, is freely promiſed in the new Covenant it ſelfe to be given ſo, leaving all the reſt to ſtand as it did, which is, as much as if he had ſaid nothing at all; for the queſtion was never, whence the power came to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the condition of the covenant, but whether there be any at all required to make us partakers of the ſame, which by his words, he utterly denyeth; excluding ſaith by name to beany condition of the Goſpells promiſes;<note place="margin">Fide, juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taliter. Vrſ. pag. <hi>343.</hi>
                  </note> or any inſtrument laying hold on Chriſt, but only a quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. By which very ground, he hath utterly ungroun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and overthrown the maine foundation of our juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by faith in Chriſt; the condition of the covenant of grace, (in regard of us) and of all the Goſpels promiſes, a moſt pernitious and peſtilent opinion, directly againſt the truth of the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Novum ſoedus non anteceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſed ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentem condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem requirit. Ameſ.</note> and the doctrin received in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſt; and ſufficient, (if there were none other) to diſcover him to be a Seducer, and his doctrine, not to be the truth, but a new Goſpell of his owne deviſing; for the promiſes of the Goſpell of Chriſt pertain only to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, and that by reaſon of their faith in him, as appears by <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.16. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.36. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.9. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.23. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> elſe might Infidels, and all ſorts of wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ungodly perſons, claime right unto all the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Goſpell and benefits of the new Covenant (as farre as the faithfull themſelves) and that ſo continuing, it followes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="assertion">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:13575:12"/>
               <head>6. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> The Goſpel was in mans nature before the fall.</head>
               <head type="sub">Explication.</head>
               <p>THis aſſertion, only he diſclaimes, as none of his, no not in any ſenſe, throwing thereupon his wonted filth into the face of him, that objects it to him: and yet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after he confeſſeth ſome ſuch words in a letter, but in another ſenſe, which ſenſe he doth not yet declare to cleare himſelfe withall, as (no doubt) the witty man would have done, had he knowne how. But it ſeemes hee had forgotten how he confeſſed the words to me himſelfe, at the conference to this purpoſe, that, <hi>in potentiâ,</hi> it was there; that is, that mans nature was capable of it, when it ſhould be revealed, a deep ſpeculation and of as worthy conſequence, as true; for if he underſtand it of nature cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, the Scriptures teſtifie that (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>the naturall man comprehendeth not the things of the ſpirit;</hi> ſpeaking of the Goſpell,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.</note> untill hee bee enlightned by the ſpirit of God. But the myſtery of the matter, (it ſeemes) is that he would purſue the Law to the utmoſt, even into Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe it ſelfe, and chaſe it out of the heart of <hi>Adam,</hi> as that which never had any lawfull being any where; ſo bitter, was this Antinomian againſt the holy Law of God, a fearefull mind; but to proceed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="assertion">
               <head>7. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> Faith is not to be tryed, by any fruits, or ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, but only by the perſwaſion it ſelfe.</head>
               <head type="sub">Explication.</head>
               <p>THis he confeſſeth to be his owne, and explaineth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in this manner; that fruits and effects do not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13575:12"/>demonſtrateth faith to any mans owne ſoule; but faith only demonſtrates them to be the fruits and effects that attend it ſelfe; for how can any know, that faith hath ſuch fruits and effects, but by the word? and how can we know the word is truth but by faith only? thus he: wherein there is need of an other explanation to expound this; ſuch are the mazes of this mans myſteries; for firſt, the queſtion is concerning juſtifying faith, whether it hath any fruits or effects to be known by? the anſwer is given out of an hiſtoricall faith in beleeving the truth of the Scriptures: the former concernes particular aſſurance of faith and grace; the later, only the generall teſtimony of the word concerning ſuch things: wherein there is great difference; for many are perſwaded of the truth of the Scriptures, that have no aſſurance at all of their own ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; yea <hi>the very Devills, beleeve and tremble, Jam.</hi> 2.19. the one is not by grace, but by the evidence of truth, which they cannot withſtand, the other is by a ſpeciall work of the holy ſpirit; but here in this reaſon of his is layd a falſe ſuppoſition for a ground, <hi>viz.</hi> that as by a bare perſwaſion we beleeve the contents of the Scriptures to be true; ſo by a bare perſwaſion we are aſſured of the true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our faith and our owne ſalvation.<note place="margin">Vide Bucan. de Scripturâ, p. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> Whereas there are many ſtrong and ſufficient arguments and grounds to prove the truth of the holy Scriptures, beſides a bare per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion or conceit: ſo likewiſe are there many evidences and ſignes of faith in true beleevers, whereby it may bee knowne, and not by a bare perſwaſion only.</p>
               <p>For albeit we grant a certain reflect act, of ſaving faith in the true beleever, whereby he is oftentimes fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of his ſtanding in the ſtate of grace; yet withall, we affirme, that this perſwaſion is not<note n="*" place="margin">See righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mans aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance by Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> fully of this point, <hi>pag.</hi> 17.18, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> alone, but hath cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine effects, and concommitants proper to it ſelfe, wherby it may be knowne and diſtinguiſhed, or diſcerned from a groundleſſe preſumption and bare conceit, elſe may the moſt carnall perſons; yea the vileſt men, perſwade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (as often they do) of the favour of God, and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13575:13"/>to come, when there is no ſuch matter belonging to them; ſuch was the perſwaſion of thoſe Iewes, that boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted themſelves, not only to be the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but the children of God: when as our Saviour told them plainly,<note place="margin">That was ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: let theſe beware then.</note> they were the children of the divell, and proves it by their fruits, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.44. by which fruits alſo, it may be diſcerned in others: for which cauſe alſo the Holy Ghoſt referres us to examination and tryall. <hi>Examine your ſelves, whether ye be in the faith, prove your owne ſelves,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. alluding (as it were) to the touchſtone, and ſcales; or to the ſymptomes of health and ſickneſſe in the body, which needed not at all, if a bare perſwaſion were enough, being directed againſt ſuch a ſupine and overly confidence, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is that of St. <hi>James,</hi> in proving or ſhewing faith by workes, <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.26.</p>
               <p>How dangerous a doctrin then hath this man broached in the Church; by teaching men to reſt only upon a bare perſwaſion of their beleeving without any further ſearch, or tryall; withall, taxing and bitterly cenſuring, thoſe Miniſters, that in their teaching urge and require, any ſignes, fruits, or effects of faith and grace, in all, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe themſelves to be beleevers, as he doth in this manner, and in theſe very termes. <hi>They tell them</hi> (viz. the people) <hi>that they muſt take heed they be not deceived, for many are deceived with falſe faith, for true; and therefore they muſt look it be of the right</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">This is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly ſpoken</note> 
                  <hi>kind: and if it be then they tell them, that theſe, and theſe ſignes will follow; a change of the life, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe of heart, and univerſall obedience to the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of God, and ſuch like, elſe their faith is but a fancy, &amp;c. pag.</hi> 29.<note place="margin">It ſeemes then he was ſuch a beleever him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</note> Now, what kind of faith (according to this cenſure) doth this man teach his diſciples to relie upon? but according to his owne words, that without either change of life, uprightneſſe of heart, or conſcience of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the will of God; they may perſwade themſelves, they are true beleevers, and in the aſſured way of life, and ſalvation; which doctrine, if it be not moſt oppoſite to the Goſpel of Chriſt, and moſt pernitious to the ſoules of men,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13575:13"/>what is? are there any carnall wretched people, that will not eaſily ſwallow down this poyſon? ſurely if ever there were any Impoſtors in the Church this was one, but let all beware how they follow him; yet he goes on.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="assertion">
               <head>8. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> Faith is the only ſigne of ſalvation.</head>
               <head type="sub">Explication.</head>
               <p>THis he thus explaineth, that faith is the only infallible evidence to a beleevers own ſoule of his ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is all hee ſaith to it, and that not very true; for St. <hi>Iohn</hi> makes love an infallible ſigne, and evidence to a mans own ſoule of ſalvation.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>We know that we have paſſed from death to life, becauſe we love the brethren,</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.14. (which place was noted in the margin, but he would not touch it) and S. <hi>Paul</hi> makes the ſanctification of the ſpirit, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe of the truth, infallible evidences of election and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13. but theſe things are utterly againſt his Goſpell, and profeſſion both, therefore he medles not with them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="assertion">
               <head>9. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> The new Creature, is only faith in Chriſt.</head>
               <head type="sub">Explication.</head>
               <p>HIs explanation is, that the new Creature is only the true beleever in Chriſt; as if the ſubject, and the habit, the beleever, and his faith were all one, and the very ſame thing: by ſuch explanations a man may ſay any thing, which I wiſh his diſciples to obſerve, that they may ſee what gudgions they ſwallow from this new <hi>Apollo</hi> with his riddles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="assertion">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:13575:14"/>
               <head>10. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> Regeneration is not to bee tryed by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fruits, effects, or ſignes, but only by faith, wherin it conſiſteth.</head>
               <head type="sub">Explication.</head>
               <p>HErein he quarrells, firſt, at the citing of the words, as his Goſpel grounds; next that they are changed from <hi>wherby it is attained,</hi> to <hi>wherein it conſiſts;</hi> which are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but ſhifts and cavills: for the words are expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed under his owne hand, and agree with his former Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that the new creature is only faith in Chriſt: and that faith is not to be tryed by ſignes, or effects, which is the ſubſtance of what he here delivereth: and in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation he thus diſchargeth himſelfe; that, Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath no infallible tryall for a mans owne aſſurance, but only by the truth of his faith; this is his meaning, and this not very ſound; for is not every ſaving grace, every effectuall work of the holy ſpirit,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22, 23, 24.</note> every fruit of ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, proceeding from the word and ſpirit, converting the heart, a ſigne of regeneration, aſwell as faith, and wherby the tryall may be made, aſwell as by it? (inſtance was given in the grace of love, but he would not ſee it,) eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſeeing he will admit, no ſignes nor effects in the tryall of faith, but the bare perſwaſion; for after this way, if a man be ſtrongly perſwaded that he is regenerate, though there be no ſignes, fruits, or effects to ſhew it; yet he muſt reſt upon the perſwaſion, that it is ſo, howſoever, becauſe he is ſo perſwaded; but why is he ſo perſwaded, he cannot tell, neither is he to inquire after it, either in reſpect of his faith, or his regeneration; by this way, Miniſters might ſave all their labour in teaching the people, and only bid them beleeve they are in Chriſt, and then they are regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, all under one, but make no tryall of either of them, that's needleſſe, their perſwaſion is ſufficient for both. How
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13575:14"/>unlike is this Seducers doctrin; yea, how contrary to the Doctrine and Goſpell of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, wherein are ſo many exhortations to duties; ſo many cautions and preſſing admonitions to ſearch and try,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.23.</note> to prove and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine our affections and actions; our faith and our fruits, yea our very perſons, and ſpirits, leſt we deceive our ſelves with falſe imaginations of our own or the illuſions of our common enemy: the reſt of his diſcourſe is anſwered in the ſeventh Aſſertion; then to proceed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="assertion">
               <head>11. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> Sanctification is not by the ſpirit in our ſelves, but only in Chriſt; ſhewed in acts, and not in the habits of grace.</head>
               <head type="sub">Explication.</head>
               <p>THis whole aſſertion, he acknowledgeth to be his own, without any exception; wherein, (according to his words) he denyeth ſanctification by the ſpirit of God, and all habits of grace; but in what myſticall ſenſe; and in what conſtruction, his explanation will declare; which is thus. <hi>Sanctification is not in our ſelves, that is, in the fleſh, but only as we are in union with Chriſt, and by the ſpirit only, as we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it of its operations, by mortification, or quickning theſe our mortall bodies, yet not ſo in us as mingled with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, but as diſtinct abſolutely from the fleſh; as being an other nature, yea a participation of the Divine nature,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3.4.</note> 
                  <hi>which though it make up one perſon, yet is none at all, of the old man, nor of the old creation, but it is that new Creation, that new heart, and that ſpirit of God which is beſtowed upon us;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11.19.</note> 
                  <hi>which yeeldeth no new habits in the fleſh, as if that were changed or renewed, but is ſubſiſting of it ſelfe, that it is of power to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt it ſelfe, by acts of quickning, and reviving, and enabling this mortall fleſh, as the life of Ieſus in it, &amp;c. neither is it the ſanctified perſon that hath any habit of grace in his fleſh, but the Lord Jeſus dwelling in him, doth put forth the bright beames
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13575:15"/>of his glory, in ſuch vertues, as do beſt fit the time and place in which he lives,</hi> Rom. 8.9. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.8, 9.</p>
               <p>Here is his myſterie, tending as much to the edification of the people, as if he had read to them a Lecture of <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick,</hi> or caſt duſt in their eyes to make them ſee; for firſt, he denies ſanctification to be by the ſpirit in ourſelves; then he grants it to be in our ſelves, but not in the fleſh; then it is by the ſpirit as we underſtand it of his operations; yet there are no new habits in the fleſh, as if that were changed at all; but then, that it doth quicken our mortall bodies, and yet not as joyned with the fleſh, but abſolutely di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct by it ſelfe, it ſendeth forth Acts as the life of Ieſus in it, wherin he utterly denyeth regeneration, ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or any change of nature at all in the ſanctified perſon; who only is ſanctified by the preſence of Chriſt in him, (which hee calls his union with Chriſt) but not by any reall work of the ſpirit in any faculty of the ſoule, nor by any change at all wrought in the heart, but it remaines as carnall and ſenſuall, as it was before the ſpirits entrance: a ſtrange and monſtrous peece of doctrin,<note place="margin">See the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in, <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.49. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.23.</note> denying the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Articles of our Chriſtian faith, and one of the chiefeſt priviledges of a true Chriſtian, which is to be regenerate by the ſpirit of God: affirming a man to bee ſanctified without any grace or goodneſſe, but even as he was borne in <hi>puris naturalibus,</hi> and in that ſtate to have Chriſt living in him; a peſtilent and blaſphemous opinion: And that the Reader may ſee this to be his poſitive doctrin, delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately ſet down. I think meet to lay before his eyes, a ſhort tract of this point made by him of purpoſe, (as it ſeemes) to doctrinate his diſciples withall, wherin the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of this Seducers divinity is diſcloſed, and it is this that followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Its a thing to be conſidered what the new creature is,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A treatiſe of the old man and the new.</note> 
                  <hi>that new man, that ſeed of God, which is borne of the ſpirit: it is not any renovation of the old man, that which is borne of the fleſh, the fallen man, for that's from beneath, this from above; that's from the earth, this from heaven; a new creation of nothing;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13575:15"/>as in the creation of the world: ſo that the inward or new man, differ as much from the outward or old, as the godly nature of Chriſt doth differ from his manly nature; and both theſe natures together, make but one perſon as in him: this is the reaſon that he which is borne of God ſinneth not, nor can ſin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note.</note> 
                  <hi>for it is a partaking of the godly nature, and ſuch are as perfect as ever they ſhall be, (although not in manifeſtation,) and yet the old man is as imperfect, as ever it was: for the new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is not the mutation or change of the underſtanding from darkneſſe to light, for then there ſhould no darkneſſe remaine:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sound reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> à nen per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecto ad nihil.</note> 
                  <hi>nor a change of the will from crooked to ſtreight, for then ſhould no perverſeneſſe remaine; nor any ordering of the ſame affections, for ſo all diſorder were put away; nor yet a change of the memory, for ſo were the memory without defect: for, this underſtanding, will, affections, memory, and the reſt are gifts from heaven, and muſt of neceſſity be perfect, without any defect or ſuperfluity, for our firſt generation as borne of parents is totally fallen, and cannot be recovered here: but our regeneration is wholly perfect, and can never be corrupted, or ſinne againe; for take it in the parts, what is repentance, or faith, or love, or joy, or any of the reſt, are they not the gifts of God? and are not Gods gifts all perfect and without blemiſh?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">But are they ſo in us?</note> 
                  <hi>Theſe being diſtinct in our minds, as the divine, and humane natures of Chriſt in that one perſon; we ſhall not impute</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Yet <hi>David</hi> ſaid; I have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</note> 
                  <hi>our ſinnes to our ſelves, nor yet our good ſo confuſedly, as in times paſt: the fleſh or old man ſhall have no glory of any good is done, nor the ſpirit or new man, any ſhame of the evill or ſinne, that the fleſh commits; it will nt only enable us to know our owne eſtates, but the holy Scriptures; and we ſhall ſee the vanity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The beſt wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and folly, in a ground of faith.</note> 
                  <hi>and folly of the moſt (if not all) writers, who put all the work upon the change, wrought in this fleſh, which can never bee changed.</hi> So ſtrange a piece of ſtuffe, as I think need no further opening or confuting to them that have underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; but for ſuch as are blinded with partiality, I would propoſe but theſe few Quaeres to conſider off, and reſolve by Scripture.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whether the Divine and humane natures of Chriſt,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13575:16"/>be fit inſtances in this caſe: ſeeing his divine nature contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the fulneſſe of the God-head, and his humane nature was perfect and without ſpot of ſin, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.9. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. eſpecially propounding it (as he doth) without exception or difference of nature or perſons, between him and us, as if the caſe were in manner one, and the reſemblance in all things equall; which may open a gap to many blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous errors, about the union, and the natures themſelves.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether the creation of the world, of nothing, be a reſemblance in all things ſutable (as he alſo makes it) to the work of regeneration? ſeeing there was no praeexiſtent matter at all to work upon, but the very ſubſtances were created: here is matter praeexiſtent, as the underſtanding, will, and affections; only new qualities are created in them from what they had before: by which meanes the ſame fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties are made (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) the weapons of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe to God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.13.</note> that were before only the weapons of unrighteouſneſſe to ſinne; and then are not the faculties themſelves for ſubſtance ſent new from heaven as he drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, but only the old are altered.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether the flat deniall of any mutation, or change in the underſtanding, will, and affections, be not a plaine deniall of regeneration, and ſanctification by the ſpirit? and if it be; why then doth he or they talke at any time of either of them, as if they granted that they do not, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be to colour, and cloak their error with hypocriſie?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether to hold and affirme, that the underſtanding will, and affections of beleevers are<note n="*" place="margin">See the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.9. <hi>ad finem.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> perfect, as alſo their faith, love, joy, and other gifts, and that ſuch themſelves, are as perfect here, as ever they ſhall be; is not directly to oppoſe the Scriptures and all truth? yea to contradict him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who ſaith we do alwaies grow in faith, and love, and anſwerable fruits; for that which is already perfect can have no bettering: or what need have ſuch of the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted righteouſnes of Chriſt (of which theſe men talke ſo much) if they have perfection of all things in themſelves; for to the old man it muſt not be applyed, and the new man
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13575:16"/>is perfect already: ſo they overthrow the maine grounds and Articles of Chriſtian Religion, and put by any need of Chriſt himſelfe.</p>
               <p>Now the Lord deliver all his people from ſuch perniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and damnable opinions;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1.</note> more exceptions might bee taken at this rotten familiſticall treatiſe, but its irkeſome to pore on it any further, therefore I paſſe on.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="assertion">
               <head>12. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> Beleevers, when they fall into any ſin, be it adultery or murther are not to mourne or grieve, (for that ſavours of the fleſh) but ſtill to rejoyce, becauſe it is written, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce evermore;</hi> and that joy is the ſpeciall means to bring them out of their ſin.</head>
               <head type="sub">Explication.</head>
               <p>HEre is another parcell of worthy doctrine delivered <hi>vivâ voce,</hi> at a conference, and acknowledged (for the words) to be his own, ſtanding out to maintain them: only hee gives us here forſooth, a ſenſe to underſtand the words by; which is, that by ſorrow and mourning, hee intends worldly ſorrow and deſperate mourning for ſin, that beleevers are not ſo to mourne, but to retaine ſtill ſome hope in Chriſt; and this he ſaith, was all he affirmed at the conference, but that his words are perverted, which if it be ſo, then hath he (doubtleſſe) great wrong done to him; but if it be not ſo, then is he a great lyar, and Seducer both. Now for the proofe of this, not only the witneſſes preſent can teſtifie, but the paſſages themſelves do ſhew, that we profeſſedly maintained godly ſorrow for ſinne; but when hee with ingeminations denyed all ſorrow whatſoever, there was produced againſt him, firſt, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3.4. <hi>there is a time to mourn:</hi> and then that of <hi>Peter, who went out and wept bitterly, Luk.</hi> 22.62. the former he ſhifted with his wit;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13575:17"/>to the later hee replyed, that it was an inſtance that fell not out in an age, ſo that the queſtion was not about the kind of ſorrow, but of ſorrowing at all, which he oppoſed, and we maintained (but farre was it from the thoughts of any of us, to maintain worldly or deſperate ſorrow for ſin;) then the reaſon that he gave for his opinion was, that we are bid to rejoyce evermore, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.16. and that joy will bring a man beſt out of his ſinne; this is the ſubſtance of what was ſaid about this point.</p>
               <p>Therefore hath this man done wickedly in ſeeking to caſt the ſhame of his errours upon others, ſhifting cleane from what he maintained to a point of an other kind; for the colouring of which colluſion he falls on, with a long invective againſt Miniſters in generall,<note place="margin">VVhat made <hi>Saul, Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel</hi> and <hi>Iudas</hi> deſtroy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? was it Legal teaching</note> for preſſing ſo much, humiliation and ſorrow for ſinne, as the cauſe of ſo many ſelfe murthers, and miſchiefes among men, terming them Legaliſts; and their congregations pretented Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Aſſemblies, yea Iewiſh and worſe than Iewiſh Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues, with much to that effect. Wherein, if any are faulty I am not to defend it: the grace of Chriſt is ſurely, to be publiſhed plainly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39.</note> and plentifully to the people; and the threatnings to bee ſeconded with the promiſes to work true repentance in the hearts of men; elſe I beleeve, a Miniſter doth but the leaſt part of his meſſage, and the work may proſper accordingly. But what is that to this Seducer, or how is he to be beleeved in this caſe who denies any uſe of the Law at all, any terrours or feare of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, any mourning or ſorrow for ſinne, any thing ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to humiliation; only faith and joy, is that he ſtands for in a Goſpel Miniſter. Is his teſtimony to be received againſt all Miniſters in generall without exception? is<note n="*" place="margin">Being the way of the falſe prophet, and falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</note> his way to bee obſerved in an extreamity of farre more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous conſequence? for without all mourning and ſorrow for ſinne, what need is there of the comforts of the Goſpel; what applying of Chriſt at all? who came only to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the mourners, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 61.1, 2, 3. and calls ſuch unto him as travell, and are heavy laden, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. yea in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13575:17"/>themſelves that fall into ſinne, this is required, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.17. and the holy Scriptures commend this unto the Saints for ever, as that which worketh repentance to ſalvation, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10. how ſinfull then is this mans do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and pernitious to the ſoules of men? who denies all ſorrowing for the fouleſt crimes, teaching men to impute it only to the old man in them, and not to themſelves, when they fall into wickedneſſe: but there is more remaining.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="assertion">
               <head>13. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> Careleſſe Chriſtians are the choiſeſt belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, becauſe they depend wholly upon Chriſt.</head>
               <head type="sub">Explication.</head>
               <p>THis Aſſertion may be known by his livery, to whom he belongs; even the careleſſe maſter we laſt menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned; who like himſelfe would have all his followers to be careleſſe alſo, and they are his choiſe beleevers: who ever preſcribed ſuch rules of looſeneſse, for men to live by, unleſse it were <hi>Epicurus</hi> himſelfe, the chiefe of Libertines? but it is worſe in this man, in that he ſeekes to ground them on faith, and the rules of the Goſpell; for thus he tells us; that careleſse is here taken in a holy ſenſe, belonging only to thoſe that depend on Chriſt, becauſe they will not bee negligent in the uſe of the meanes: (which clauſe he ſaith, ſhould have beene added to his Aſsertion) to which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that the Engliſh word careleſse cannot properly be ſo taken; ſeeing it ſignifieth with us a regardleſse mind, not heeding or eſteeming ſuch or ſuch a matter, and is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally taken in the worſt ſenſe; as when we ſay a careleſse man, we intend one that regards not his manner of life;<note place="margin">Like <hi>Gallio</hi> in the Iewes matters. <hi>Acts</hi> 18.17.</note> or a careleſse Chriſtian, one that regards not Chriſtian duties; in which generall ſenſe he takes it, as comprehending all that concernes either ſoule or body, this life or the next; in all which, men muſt be careleſse, yea in reſpect of all ſins,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13575:18"/>and duties, which is to be a wretchleſse perſon caring for nothing.</p>
               <p>And whereas he ſends us to the Scriptures for the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of his word, which forbid al carefulneſse in any thing, as <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.7. to that I anſwer, that the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall word in thoſe places, doth not ſignifie all care, heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſse, or providence in any ſenſe to condemne it;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp;c.</note> but only a wringing, perplexing, and diſtruſtfull care, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from unbeleefe, the ſame that in <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.31. <hi>take no thought;</hi> which is not oppoſed to careleſneſse, but to that lawfull and provident care,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Pro.</hi> 10.4. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.15.</note> commended in the Scriptures, under the name of providence, watchfulnes, heed taking, and diligence; all which, accompany faith, as concurring with the promiſes and providence of God; yet, might an improper word have beene borne withall, did not the reſt of this mans rudiments, give juſt occaſion of ſuſpecting his words, eſpecially being ſtrange and affected.</p>
               <p>Concerning his complaint: that his words are not fully expreſsed; I ſay they are ſo ſet down, under his own hand, as in the Aſsertion, which is more than was at firſt, (as one of his followers told me) that, being only this; careleſse Chriſtians,<note place="margin">If he deny this it is but like all the. reſt.</note> are the choiſeſt beleevers: but to leave this care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſse counſell, with thoſe choiſe beleevers, and paſse on to the next.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="assertion">
               <head>14. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> To doubt of the favour of God, after ſinne committed, is worſe than the ſin it ſelfe.</head>
               <head type="sub">Explication.</head>
               <p>THis Aſsertion is ſet down in his own words, and yet he quarrells at it, and tells us that in ſome other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces theſe words are inſerted <hi>[nouriſhed by true beleevers]</hi> which are ſtollen out to expoſe his ſaying to deriſion: to which I anſwer; firſt, that his Goſpell grounds and other aſsertions, are ſo full of variations, and contradictions,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13575:18"/>that nothing can be alleadged out of one place, without ſome ground of cavilling from another; which was his cunning to help out by ſhifts and evaſions, as need requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; but what need any man ſteale, where there is ſuch ſtore of good ſtuffe as in his rudiments. Secondly, admit theſe words, <hi>doubtings nouriſhed, &amp;c.</hi> yet, doth it not help him that condemnes all doubtings in ſuch, ſimply, without limitation, as being the fruits of unbeleefe, the greateſt ſin under the Goſpell; for the nouriſhing of doubtings doth but aggravate what in it ſelfe is evill.</p>
               <p>To the point them, I ſay, that although doubtings pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from unbeleefe ſimply conſidered, are great evills, and to be ſtriven againſt, by true beleevers: yet in ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes as we ſpeak of; revolts and relapſes into foule and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous ſins of the ſame or other kinds, by ſuch as profeſſe themſelves to be beleevers; there is ſomewhat more to be conſidered: for firſt, as concerning the fact it ſelfe, it is certaine the Lord doth not favour evill, but abhorre it, though in his own children, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.27.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For their owne parts they may well, in ſuch caſes doubt and queſtion their owne ſincerity, when their ſins are ſcandalous, and often committed, ſeeing there is not faith nor grace ſufficient to withſtand their luſts, but they live in them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.18. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.9.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They may well doubt and queſtion the favour of God towards them, if not in the main, yet for the preſent in this particular, of a ſcandalous ſin till it be repented of, and ſo forgiven, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 32.3. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 38.3. ſo that in ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſome doubtings are not only lawfull, but expedient, and neceſſary, our hearts being deceitfull; but againſt all theſe conſiderations, utterly to condemn all doubtings in the caſe of ſcandalous ſinning, without any limitation of the ſins, or time of continuance in them, as he doth, how dangerous a thing it is? for hereby that may eaſily come to paſſe, which the Lord ſo vehemently proteſted againſt in his people, to ſwear falſly, to ſteale, murther, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit adultery, &amp; ſuch like, &amp; come into the houſe of God and ſay they are delivered, to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13575:19"/>doe ſuch abominations, which are called lying words. <hi>Ier.</hi> 7.8. as alſo that fearefull ſtate of the preſumptuous ſinner deſcribed, <hi>Deut:</hi> 29.19. which comes by ſuch flattering and bleſſing a mans ſelfe in his heart, when his deeds are wicked,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ide. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.2.</note> whereunto this mans doctrine tendeth as the event alſo hath ſhewed in ſome of his followers, ſtanding more upon their mirth and confidence than any feare of ſinne, or care of obedience, rejecting alſo all mourning and ſorrow for ſinnes committed, as not agreeing with Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian profeſſion. But there is more following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="assertion">
               <head>15. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> It is as eaſie to beleeve remiſſion of ſins, as to make confeſſion of them.</head>
               <head type="sub">Explication.</head>
               <p>ALL is eaſie to this man, who hath found out an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier way to heaven (if wee may beleeve him) than ever was knowne before, or is ſafe to follow now. Its as eaſie to beleeve remiſſion of ſinnes as to make confeſſion of them. But how doth he explaine this Oracle? ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (it ſeemes) ſome flaw in the matter, he hath altered the words,<note place="margin">True confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends the other. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.9.</note> and inſteed of confeſſion, hath put in, truly asking forgiveneſſe, thinking this will hold better, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his reaſon, becauſe both are the gifts of God, truly to beleeve and truly to ask pardon; but if there be no ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar matter in it, why doth he ſet it out as a Goſpell ground and ſingular rudiment of his owne? unleſſe it be to make ſimple people beleeve, that it is as eaſie for them to obtain remiſſion of ſinnes, and to bee aſſured of it, as to ſay; Lord have mercy upon them, on their death bedds. Which they are too apt unto, without his directions: but for the point as he would hold it, notwithſtanding both thoſe are the gifts of God, and a like eaſie for him to effect, yet in regard of our ſelves, in whom theſe gifts muſt work, I ſuppoſe it a farre harder matter truly to apply the promiſes
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13575:19"/>and to beleeve that our ſinnes are remitted, than to confeſſe them, and ask forgiveneſſe of them, becauſe in the former there is reaſon, and all, oppoſing; but in the later, the power of conſcience, the ſenſe of wrath, and feare of danger doe all concurre with the ſpirit in that act, in ſo much as wee may read of ſome that have truly confeſſed their ſinnes, and craved pardon for them,<note place="margin">One deſines faith to bee a wonderfull grace.</note> that yea could not preſently beleeve, nor bee aſſured in their hearts; they were pardoned, and remitted to them. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 31.10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.6. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 77.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88.14. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it being a ſpeciall act of Gods ſpirit to perſwade his people of their reconciliation, and his love towards them in Chriſt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, this conceit of the eaſineſſe of faith doth ſeeme to be maintained by ſuch as never had it, nor knew truly, what it is to be truly and comfortably perſwaded of the favour of God, and the pardon of ſin, againſt all the diſputes of reaſon, and the conſcience together. But to haſten.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="assertion">
               <head>16. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> Chriſt is involved in every proverb of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Explication.</head>
               <p>THis Aſſertion (as he ſaith) needeth no explanation at all; only to juſtifie the truth, wee muſt take this Argument from him.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>The wiſdome or power of God is involved in every Proverb of <hi>Salomon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſt is that wiſdome and power of God <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>1.24. Ergo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>Let the Reader here take notice, that at the conference when this Aſſertion was diſcuſſed, wee propounded this ſenſe to him; that as Chriſt was the wiſdome of God; ſo he might be ſaid to be involved in the Proverbs of <hi>Salomon,</hi> wherein his wiſdome ſhineth. But not as hee is a ſacrifice for ſinne, in which ſenſe he maintained it; but that former he utterly rejected as not ſufficient, yet now hee makes it
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13575:20"/>his owne and his only Argument, to convince (as he ſaith) the Accuſer. Theſe are the common tricks of this Seducer, for had he reſted on the former ſenſe, we had not at all dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferd.</p>
               <p>Now the ground hee then layed was, <hi>that to him give all the Prophets witneſſe. Acts</hi> 10.43. <hi>John</hi> 5.39. but <hi>Salomon</hi> was a Prophet; <hi>Ergo,</hi> he is involved in every Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb of his: which how well it followeth I need not ſhew to them that have underſtanding, for neither do the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets in every part of their propheſies ſo mention Chriſt; (having many other hiſtoricall matters inſerted for the time) nor yet <hi>Salomon,</hi> who though he ſpeak of Chriſt in the 8. and 9. Chapters <hi>&amp;c</hi> yet not in every proverb of his (if in any) in that ſenſe, but of other morall matters, and wholſome counſells neceſſary to bee knowne in their place. Why then this man ſhould produce ſuch a poſition, not knowne before, I ſee not, unleſſe to perſwade his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of a greater inſight he had in the Scriptures than other men (being moſt vain-glorious) and to carry the palme for a Preacher of Chriſt. But it followes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="assertion">
               <head>17. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> The 15. <hi>Pſal.</hi> is only a deſcription of Chriſt: and the beatitudes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. only belong to him; and to no man, that ever was or ſhall be, becauſe all men are vanitie.</head>
               <head type="sub">Explication.</head>
               <p>THe perfections (he ſaith) required in the 15 <hi>Pſal.</hi> and in all other Scriptures of like nature, are not, nor ſhall bee found in any man, but by their union with Chriſt, for that all men ſeverd from Chriſt are vanity, for proofe whereof he citeth <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1, 2. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30 this is his full explanation, wherein hee hath alſo kept his cuſtome of fraud and deceit, as before, for this ſenſe was then propounded unto him that the 15. <hi>Pſalme</hi> was a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13575:20"/>not of unregenerate perſons, but of beleevers, &amp; ſuch as in the phraſe of Scripture were ſtiled righteous men, to whom the promiſes of life (through Chriſt) did appertaine;<note place="margin">There were witneſſes enough of this.</note> but this hee utterly rejected with theſe words, <hi>no man, no man, that ever was, or would bee:</hi> the like alſo he affirmed of <hi>Pſa.</hi> 119.1. and <hi>Matth.</hi> the 5th. and now he comes and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints us that all our perfections are by our union with Chriſt, and without him we are vanity, which is his ground. Is not this to dally with the word of God, and to mock and abuſe his ſervants? the queſtion being whether thoſe deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions belonged to any men in any ſenſe; which he denyed, referring them only unto Chriſt, which now hee ſeeks to ſhift off with an evaſion.</p>
               <p>But it is to be ſuſpected that in all this, he hath a further meaning, than he is willing to diſcloſe, which is, that Chriſt (of whom he ſpeaks) is but the new Creature, or new man in us, who is endued with ſuch perfections, that he is able of himſelfe, to ſend forth bright beames of glory, and to act, ſuch acts of grace in us, as are proper to his nature, in whom are all things perfect, aſwell faculties, as gifts; ſeeing he uſeth the ſame phraſes (as before) of union, and perfection, and then is his ſenſe moſt corrupt, familiſticall, and abominable, for which ſee what is written on the 11. Aſſertion. It followes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="assertion">
               <head>18. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> The ſaying of <hi>Salomon; Rejoyce in the wife of thy youth,</hi> is not meant of a mans wife, but of Chriſt; becauſe he can ſatisfie us at all times.</head>
               <head type="sub">Explication.</head>
               <p>THis is a branch of the former Aſſertion, that Chriſt is involved in every Proverb of <hi>Salomon,</hi> therefore in this place, which he alſo calleth a Proverb; though (I ſuppoſe) unfitly, and explaines himſelfe thus: that no man in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits ſenſe, can rejoyce, but by his joy in Chriſt, and that hee
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13575:21"/>alone can ſatisfie us, &amp;c. wherin, firſt, he hath altered and perverted the meaning of the Scripture, and the purpoſe of the holy Ghoſt, which is dehorting men from ſtrange wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to direct them (as a remedy) to the love of their own,<note place="margin">He never cites nor regards any expoſitors.</note> and to delight in them; which he turnes over into a myſticall meaning to Chriſt, and ſo puts by the object intended. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, to colour the matter, he tells us of the ground of our ſpirituall rejoycing, that it is only by our joy in Chriſt; which is collaterall, and nothing to the queſtion, becauſe that in the exhortation; naturall, and conjugall affections ſeaſoned with grace, are required in the husband to his wife: he is to love her,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 5.19. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> as his wife, and that with an entire affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, delighting in her, yea erring in her love as the Text is, to which purpoſe is that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.29.31. all intended to the ſame duty, which to turne over only to a ſpirituall affection, and that unto Chriſt, is, with familiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call allegories to abuſe and not interpret the Scriptures: yet, thirdly, to juſtifie his Aſſertion, in comparing the wife un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt; he alleadgeth that, in <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.14. where the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant it ſelfe (as he ſaith) is called the wife of youth, which how proper it is, and pertinent to the matter, I leave to the learned to judge; for my part I conceive it to be directly oppoſite to this his opinion, and his practiſe alſo in his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with his own wife, which, (as I have heard) was none of the beſt. But for this worthleſſe Aſſertion, it had not at all beene mentioned, but to ſhew his abuſe of Scripture by his interpretations which is frequent with him, as when hee alſo affirmed, theſe words: <hi>Out of his belly ſhall flow Rivers of living water, Ioh.</hi> 7.38. to be taken out of thoſe of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; Drink waters out of thine owne Ciſterne, Pro.</hi> 5.15. all which his followers take up with admiration, wondring at the ſublimity of the mans underſtanding: but heare fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="assertion">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:13575:21"/>
               <head>19. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> It is too great preſumption for any Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, to undertake the expoſition of any whole book in the Scriptures, becauſe he cannot ſhew how Chriſt is involved in every part.</head>
               <head type="sub">Explication.</head>
               <p>AS in warres, beſides the maine preparations there are uſually appointed ſome ſuccours and ſupplies to be in ſtore, if need require: ſo hath this cunning man cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſuccours in his polemicall proceedings to help him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe withall; for wheras he had affirmed (as one of his grounds) that Chriſt is involved in every ſentence of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and in every Proverb of <hi>Salomon;</hi> leſt he ſhould be taken tripping in his expoſitions, and unable to ſhew what he maintaines; he tells us, that yet perhaps it may not bee ſhewed, nor proved in many places, and for that cauſe it is a very great preſumption to meddle with thoſe places at all, or to adventure upon the expoſition of any whole book in the Bible: by which meanes he thinkes to ſtave off, the incroaching of the enemy, and to ſave (at leaſt) his credit, at any time, which device and skill hee alſo ſheweth in defence of moſt of his Tenents. But if it be ſo, that no Scriptures may be handled by Goſpell Miniſters, ſave only ſuch, as ſpeak directly and immediatly of Chriſt, as the great ſacrifice for ſinne; then, a great part of ſome whole bookes in the Bible may not be medled withall; as of the book of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> of <hi>Samuel,</hi> of the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles, Ezra, Nehemiah, Eſter, Iob,</hi> moſt of the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> much of the Prophets, and generally all thoſe paſſages that are meerely hyſtoricll for that time, and of morall uſe, of which there is much every where diſperſed, not in the Old reſtament alone but in the New.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:13575:22"/>
So that according to this mans opinion, a great part of the holy Scriptures are penned in vaine,<note place="margin">The Acts moſt of the Epiſtle of <hi>Iames,</hi> and of the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </note> and might have been ſpared; for if they tended not to edification, to what purpoſe are they? and if they doe edifie, why may they not be expounded to the Church? morall directions, rules of obedience, hiſtoricall narrations, propheſies of things to come, examples, and ſuch like, have their place and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uſe in the Church, and are to bee opened and unfolded to the people for edification, for reprehenſion, for imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as neceſſary dependances on the myſtery of Chriſt. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the whole Scripture is profitable ſaith the Apoſtle 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. and if this be ſo, why is it preſumption in any man, to meddle with all ſuch Scriptures in which the Sacrifice of Chriſt is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely mentioned? or why is it beyond their line and meaſure? but that this Seducer muſt have a way by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and out of one abſurdity to conclude another. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="assertion">
               <head>20. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> Every true beleever (howſoever it ſeemes) doth alwayes grow in faith and love, and anſwerable fruits.</head>
               <head type="sub">Explication.</head>
               <p>THe very queſtioning of the truth of this point makes the man to ſtamp and ſtartle: proclayining to all the world, that this truth ſhall ſtand, and ſtare for ever in the Accuſers face, to his ſhame here, and condemnation here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, without repentance; calling the contrary, no leſſe than blaſphemy, with ſuch other expreſſions of his well temperd zeale.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp;c.</note> But for the matter it ſelfe (leaving his rage and choller.) to what purpoſe doth the Scripture ſo often inculcate that exhortation of growing in grace, 2. <hi>Peter</hi> 3.18. of increaſing in knowledge, <hi>Coloſſians</hi> 1.10. of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing in love, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.10. of increaſing in zeale. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.19. and withall ſo earneſtly dehorting, from all
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13575:22"/>declinings, back-ſlidings, and withdrawings, in faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.12 in the power of the ſpirit. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.19. in the uſe of the meanes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.25. If there be no danger, nor poſſibilitie of decreaſing, but that of neceſſitie we do, and muſt grow in all theſe things, and the anſwerable fruits of them? are all thoſe exhortations in vaine? did not <hi>Salomon</hi> much decline in his later time from what hee was before, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.4.9. are not the Epheſians tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for leaving their firſt love, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.4. and the Sardians for languiſhing in grace, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.2. why then doth this man make ſuch an outcry at the matter? if it be but que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned whether beleevers doe alwayes grow in faith, and love, and the anſwerable fruits? and why did he not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex ſome anſwer to theſe teſtimonies of Scripture ſo direct againſt his opinion, of which he ſpeaks not a word. Is his <hi>ipſe dixit,</hi> ſufficient to carry all matters?</p>
               <p>But yet he pretends notwithſtanding ſome grounds for what he holds in the generall, as that, ſuch are planted by living waters, their root is living, and Chriſt doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually water them, their courſe is as the Sunne, and they have the promiſe of increaſing: which though it doth not alwayes appeare outwardly, yet inwardly it is done. To which I therefore anſwer and that out of the ſame reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances, that neither doth every herb, or plant, or tree, continually thrive or grow, or beare fruit thats ſo planted: nor yet is the fault in the influences of heaven,<note place="margin">the tree is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blamed. <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.6.</note> the vigour of the Sunne, the ſweetneſſe of the raine, or the goodneſſe of the mould, that they are defective; but there are certain obſtructions and evill affections (as I may call them) in ſome individualls, that may hinder and ſtop the courſe of nature in them for a time; alſo there are ſtemmes of Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that keep in their fruits during that ſeaſon: ſo is it in theſe by reaſon of ſome ſpirituall obſtructions and evill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, that ſometimes poſſeſse them: as alſo a chilling Winter that oftentimes blowes over them: their perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all growth in grace, and fruitbearing,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.11.12.</note> is often hindred and ſtopped for a time: though they have ſtill life remaining
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13575:23"/>in the root, and Chriſt is the ſame to them in himſelf, as ever he was. For what reaſon elſe can be given of the former inſtances? its certain they did not grow, but rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline for a ſeaſon, yet all thoſe promiſes belonged to them, aſwell as to others. It is replyed that then they grow in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in unſeene fruits: to which I anſwer, that neither is that certain, if he meane every moment of time. For wherein did <hi>David</hi> grow all the time he lay in his ſinne? or <hi>Salomon</hi> in his ſtate of declining; or any of the reſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned? if it be ſaid in humilitie; I anſwer let that appeare:<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.8. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 20.13. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.10.</note> while <hi>David</hi> was numbring the people (which was nine moneths, and twentie dayes in doing) did hee grow in humility, or <hi>Hezekiah</hi> when hee entertained ſo vain-gloriouſly the Babyloniſh Embaſſadours, did he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly increaſe in that grace? the Text is evident to the contrary in both: for <hi>David</hi> judged himſelfe afterwards for the pride of his heart, and ſo did <hi>Hezekiah</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.26. but hereby was a foundation layed for humility to come, and then they all thrived more in grace, and in the true knowledge of themſelves,<note place="margin">As the Eagle when ſhe hath caſt her bill. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.5.</note> as the trees after winter, and the body after healing of ſome diſeaſe, which is ſufficient though they doe not alwayes grow, and doth abundantly diſcover the life of Chriſt in them, and the power of God, according to the truth of his promiſe towards them.</p>
               <p>Now what blaſphemy is in all this, that the man ſhould make ſuch an outcry at the matter and threaten damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on without repentance to him that holds ſuch an opinion, eſpecially hee having ſo notably croſſed himſelfe (as hee hath) in another poſition: affirming that a man may bee a true beleever, and yet for a time, have neither humility, love,<note place="margin">This is his owne, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny it.</note> truſt, or any other grace bud forth in practice. For if a beleever doth alwayes grow, in each of theſe with their anſwerable fruits: then how can ſuch be true belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, that have not ſo much as a bud of any of theſe in their practice at all? they are farre from fruits that have not ſo much as buds upon them. This ſentence (I ſuppoſe) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves that heavy cenſure more juſtly than the former, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13575:23"/>is farre more derogatory to the ſufficiency of the grace of Chriſt, than that. But its endles to trace this man in his mazes, being ſo intricate, and full of contradictions. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I paſſe on.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="assertion">
               <head>21. <hi>ASSERTION.</hi> No man can ſay, he doth love his brother, till he hath laid downe his life for him: neither can we our ſelves ſay, wee love the brethren, but we may ſay of others, that they doe. So expounding, 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.14.</head>
               <head type="sub">Explication</head>
               <p>TO this hee ſaith, that no man can truly ſay hee doth love his brother, till hee hath triall of his own love; neither may beleevers ſay, without vaine oſtentation, that they do ſo; but yet they may perceive that others doe ſo, and that of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> is to bee underſtood in that ſenſe; this is his explanation whrein he keeps his wonted manner of contradiction. For firſt he tells us; that no man can truly ſay he loves his brother, till he hath triall of his love, (which is by death.) Secondly, that beleevers cannot ſay at all (without oſtentation) that they doe ſo, which oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is forbidden <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.27. by which it followes that it is not lawfull for any man at all to ſay he truly loves his brother, untill he be dead, &amp; then (I ſuppoſe) he will hardly be able to ſay it, that any ſhall heare him; yet if he could ſpeak ſo, when he is dead, it muſt be vaine oſtentation too, and ſo never lawfull at all. But why muſt it be vain oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation for a beleever (on any occaſion) to profeſſe his love unto the Saints? the Prophet <hi>David</hi> openly profeſsed it <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.3. I beleeve without any vaine oſtentation; ſo doth Saint <hi>Paul</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.15. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.8. and ſo doth <hi>Peter</hi> unto our Lord. <hi>Iohn</hi> 21.17. and is not taxed with any vaine oſtentation in it, may we aſsure our hearts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13575:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>God of a good eſtate hereby (as Saint <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks) and yet not mention it to our comfort before men?<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.19.</note> but why doth hee not hold the like of faith alſo: for therein hee will have men to truſt, without any ſignes or fruits, onely upon the perſwaſion it ſelfe, and to profeſſe it. Which ſavours farre more of oſtentation than the other, and is ſo taxed by St. <hi>James, Chap.</hi> 2.20. But for that of the Apoſtle <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.27. its only intended againſt all glorying in the ſight of God in regard of works or grace in the caſe of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, which is not queſtioned here, nor ought, that way. It's a very vaine cavill.</p>
               <p>But that conceit, of knowing that others have this love in them, and not our ſelves, is beyond all imagination of any reaſonable man. For ſeeing love is a grace that may be counterfeited (as well as any other,) and that all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſeemings may be there, and in them; in whom the grace it ſelfe is not in truth: how can any be certainly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of anothers ſincerity herein;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 1.24. Spoken ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſively. As 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.39.</note> unleſſe, by an all-ſeeing knowledge (proper only unto God) I ſee not neither doe I think was ever maintained, till this paradoxicall man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan it, with his other, ſtrange deviſes. But this particular (it ſeemes) is a branch of his former phantaſie, that one may know, certainly, anothers election, by an ordinary way, and that infallibly. Which point (as I have heard) he preſſing on a time upon another of ſome rank to ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate himſelfe, as knowing his election. The party, taking him at the advantage, replyed; that if I be ſuch a one, and able ſo to diſcerne of another; then my judgement, is that M. <hi>Thraske</hi> is a phantaſticall Fellow. So he was caught in his owne net.</p>
               <p>And thus much of theſe worthy Aſſertions, which I have gone over not ſo much to ſatisfie or inſtruct thoſe that have underſtanding (the points being ſo groſſe) as to diſcover his fraud and deceit that ſeekes to cloke, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them with his miſts, that they may not be perceived of any: eſpecially, thoſe weaklings, which have beene tranſported by him, may no longer take Mercury, for
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13575:24"/>meat, I meane falſe and dangerous Doctrine, for true and wholſome food of the ſoule. Wherein all may ſee, how juſtly he hath taxed ſuch for ſlanderers, and falſe accuſers that have charged him withholding the fore-named opinions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="cautions">
               <head>Concerning the five Cautions.</head>
               <p>UNto the Aſſertions before rehearſed, there were an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed alſo (becauſe of the deceitfulnes of the Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer) certaine Cautions to the Reader, as to beware. 1. Of his Contradictions in his various Goſpel grounds. 2. Of his fallatious interpretations of Scripture. 3. Of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations. 4. Of his riddles. 5. Of his fawning, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticing ſpeeches; the diſcovery whereof hath made him to ſtartle as a malefactor hid in the dark, the light approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. For as a man ſuddenly awakened in a diſtemper, hee falls to rayling, and raving at him that's next him: vent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing little elſe than foule language, and lyes. Which are beſt anſwered with ſilence. Yet leſt this ſhould be deemed only an evaſion. I anſwer briefly.</p>
               <p>To the firſt: If the inſtances there given be not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> let the Reader look back upon the Aſſertions. And ſee how well they doe accord, eſpecially the ſecond, and the twentieth, as he hath expounded them.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond. Let all his writings, and this very book,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> be witneſſe how ſoundly he interpreteth, and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the holy Scriptures, eſpecially his 16 and 17 Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, differing from all Expoſitors.</p>
               <p>To the third, about his proteſtations,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the very inſtance it ſelfe, is ſufficient to ſhew his unfaithfulnes, compared with all his opinions.</p>
               <p>To the fourth, about his riddles,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> let the inſtances them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſhew the truth of what I alledge.<note place="margin">He hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely altered his own words.</note> Elſe why doth he ſuppreſſe the words I had ſet downe, and ſubſtitute others
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13575:25"/>in their roome. But moſt wickedly, and preſumptuouſſy hath he paralelled, the high, and holy myſteries of Chriſt, and his Goſpel, with his owne deceitfull riddles, juſtifying the one, by the other.</p>
               <p>To the fift, about his fawning; let all his acquaintance ſpeak what language he commonly uſed, till he was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked; yea, what Crocodiles teares hee would often ſhed, to gaine his prey, and to deceive the ſimple. But for his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolencie and pride, let his rude, and unſeemly demeanour towards his (then) Soveraigne Lord King <hi>James:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vſing the terms of <hi>Thou,</hi> and <hi>Thee</hi> 32 times, in one Letter to him.</note> his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronting of all men with his private opinions: his lofty and arrogant ſpeeches of himſelfe: his ſcornfull detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in this book: yea, the <hi>ſumma totalis</hi> of the man, and the matter, teſtifie, and declare, for had there beene true humility, theſe things had never beene ſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="rule_of_faith">
               <head>Of his Rule of faith.</head>
               <p>COncerning his Rule of faith. Which hee hath added by way of ſupplement, to the end of his book, it ſhewes only that he was ſick of pride, &amp; would have vented ſome extraordinary matter if he had knowne what;<note place="margin">VVherein are ſome very ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitious paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</note> for after a long and tedious preamble, promiſing wonders; hee hath at laſt produced an ordinary, and well known truth. That Chriſt Ieſus is the King, Prieſt, and Prophet of his Church. But how to apply this underſtandingly to all points of faith whatſoever (as he pretends) to give ſatisfaction, doth not there appeare; neither will it ſtand with his owne enormous Divinitie, before handled. Further, I need not meddle with it.</p>
               <p>But for concluſion, I would gladly admoniſh (if they would be admoniſhed) all the followers and admirers of this man, before they follow him any further, to conſider ſtriouſly with themſelves theſe few things, upon the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:13575:25"/>
Firſt, the evill condition, and quality of the man him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, diſcovered in divers enormities of the fou leſt nature, as, lying in the higheſt degree, rayling, ſcoffing, laſcivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, audatious perverting of Scripture, levity and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancie, turning from one opinion to another, as the yeare turned about, but never ſetling in the truth. All which are moſt unbeſeeming a man that took upon him to be the only Patron of the truth, and finder out of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the Goſpel, the Lord never<note n="*" place="margin">They are veſſels of choiſe. <hi>Acts</hi> 9.15.</note> uſing ſuch inſtruments for ſuch purpoſes.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the dangerous nature of the opinions them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as, Firſt, concerning the uſe of the moral. Law of God, that the ſame is utterly abrogated, and made void, by the comming in of the Goſpell: Secondly, that there is no regeneration or ſanctification by the ſpirit of God, nor any habits of Grace at all: Thirdly, that there is no place for repentance, humiliation, or ſorrow for ſinne in a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever, but all joy: Fourthly, that there is no triall of faith or grace by any ſignes or fruits, but only a reſting upon a bare perſwaſion: Fifthly, that men muſt be comforted in their faith, though they have neither change of life, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe of heart, nor conſcience of obedience to the Commandements of God; all which, with their depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants are very dangerous points to follow.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, his manner of maintaining and defending his Aſſertions, which is, with evident forcing of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and manifeſt contradictions with himſelfe; inſtance in that about growth in grace. Aſſertion the 20th. but chiefly in that of the Law, ſtanding in this manner.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Law is a rule of the fleſh.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Law is not to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to beleevers by Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell Miniſters.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Law did once diſcover ſinne, it doth ſo no more.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:13575:26"/>
                     <hi>There is no commiſſion at all, to preach the Law, now under the Goſpell.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Law hath nothing at all to doe with belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:13575:25"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Law is the very rule of love.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Law is of plentifull uſe to true beleevers.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Law diſcovers the greatneſſe of ſinne.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Law is of uſe to the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13575:26"/>and unholy.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Apoſtles preached the Law as ſubordinate to the Gospell.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Beleevers have moſt of all to doe with the Law.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Which how to reconcile is paſt my skill, or (I ſuppoſe) his own, but that hee would very like a <hi>Proteus</hi> as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion was offered, and turne in and out for advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, that hee will admit no difference betweene preſſing of duties, as fruits of faith, and preaching of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification by works; whereupon he cenſures all ſuch Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, (as doe the former) for Legaliſts,<note place="margin">This is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with his followers.</note> and Iuſtitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: a very groſſe and abſurd collection, directly oppoſite to the preaching of the very Apoſtles; for although it be true that neither the Law, nor duties are to be preſſed in a legall way to beleevers,<note n="*" place="margin">For which ſee Mr. <hi>Edward Reinelds</hi> of the uſe of the Law.</note> yet in an Evangelicall way, they both may and ought, Chriſt being the ground of all: which being layed, in all doctrines and exhortations thoſe inferences flow naturally from the ſame, and are to be received and obeyed of every beleever; for ſuch was the Apoſtles method and way, after matters and grounds of faith, to inferre exhortations to duties, and matters of practiſe, all flowing from the ſame root, which is Chriſt, into whom,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.5. Sec. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.8.</note> whoſoever is truly ingrafted he will be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full through his grace, guided by the word requiring and importing both, aſwell faith, as practiſe; and by this kind of teaching have thoſe many thouſand ſoules beene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted that have beene wonne unto Chriſt theſe many yeeres, and not by the wild, and dangerous way, devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by this Seducer, according to the points before diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; concerning which I may truly ſay as one ſayd once, of a gainefull, but tempting calling hee was in; that it was a good calling to live by, but perillous to die by; ſo is this a pleaſant opinion to live by, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13575:26"/>to die by; which I wiſh I may not prove to their coſt, that follow it to their end;<note place="margin">I have heard of one that much bewail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſame, on his death bed.</note> to which purpoſe I have annexed this ſhort admonition, which I wiſh and deſire may be no otherwiſe taken, than it is intended, that is Chriſtianly, and lovingly; which the Lord grant through his grace in Chriſt, to whom be glory for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <trailer>Ecce autem alterum.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:13575:27"/>
            <head>¶ A Short Advertiſement con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> RICE BOYE, as a Paralell to the former.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Maſter <hi>Boye</hi> having publiſhed a very judicious peece of work, about abſolute prayer for temporall bleſſings, ſtiled <hi>The Importunate Beggar</hi> (which was fully anſwered) to ſhew himſelfe an importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate wrangler, hee ſends forth his Reply to the ſaid anſwer, containing a very Rhapſodie of falſities, fooliſh retortions, and groundleſſe conceits, full of perſonall defamations, and detractions, with little elſe in it, which therefore to anſwer againe, were to be like himſelfe, neither needs it.<note n="*" place="margin">He puts all on a tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry faith.</note> 
               <hi>debile funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum fefellit opus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Only whereas hee is pleaſed by way of <hi>Quaere</hi> to point out his judgement, in a matter of ſome conſequence, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the meaning of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91. as if it ſecured all true beleevers from the Peſtilence, (as a branch of his opinion about temporalls) I am willing thereunto to returne, ſome anſwer, (if leave may be given, whereunto I ſubmit) not ſo much to ſatisfie a perverſe and fooliſh man wedded to his owne conceits: as to ſettle and reſolve the mindes of any ſincere and humble Chriſtians, that are therein doubtfull, conſidering the uncomfortableneſſe of the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in this time of viſitation: which hath ſorrow enough in it ſelfe, though it bee not furthered by mens errours. Briefly then I anſwer.</p>
            <p>If it doe appeare that the promiſes contained in that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13575:27"/>
               <hi>Pſalme</hi> are not litterally to be underſtood, but in a myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſenſe: then that collection concerning the certain ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption of any from the danger of the Plague, cannot be grounded on that Scripture; but that the ſame is not litte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to be underſtood, appeares by theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe the whole <hi>Pſalme</hi> (in a manner) is meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoricall, wherein there is mention of the wings and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Almighty; of his arrowes: of the hands of Angels: of the ſnare of the hunter: of treading upon the Lion, Dragon, and Aſpe. Things not properly ſo to bee taken; nor in that manner ever accompliſhed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe the promiſes all along according to the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cannot be ſo applyed, nor expected, as for inſtance.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>That ſuch as truſt in God ſhall not daſh their foot againſt a ſtone.</hi> verſe 12.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The peſtilence ſhall not come nigh them</hi> verſe 7. <hi>no not neere their dwelling.</hi> verſe 10.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>They ſhall tread upon Lions, Dragons, and Serpents</hi> verſ. 13.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>They ſhall have advancement with long life, and with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi> verſe 14, 15, 16.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For then, no true beleever in his going ſhould at any time ſtumble, or if ſo, yet not at a ſtone, as the Divell ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed it. <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.6.</p>
            <p>The peſtilence muſt not only not faſten upon their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but not ſo much as come neere their dwellings,<note n="*" place="margin">At the honſe of Mr. Doctor <hi>Chetwind</hi> in <hi>Berckley</hi> before twenty wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</note> as this fooliſh man once maintained in my hearing, out of this <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then might alſo a beleever by his faith, tread upon Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Dragons, and Aſpes, (or Adders,) without danger; alſo it would then follow that the moſt faithfull people, muſt live longeſt and be advanced in the world, contrary to the Scriptures and all experience.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe it is ſaid in the generall, that no evill at all ſhall befall ſuch, ver. 10. for ſo they muſt be exempted from all afflictions, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.6. where they are termed evills, (although by the goodneſſe of God they are turned into
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:13575:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>good to his people:) ſo that according to the letter they ſhall not at all be viſited with any loſſes, croſſes, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſorrowes; not with any mortall diſeaſes, or ſickneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as the Feaver, Conſumption or Pox; not be hurt by any deadly weapons, as ſwords, and ſpeares (eſpecially ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes) unleſſe through want of faith,<note place="margin">Verſe 5.</note> ſo that every ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier who dieth in the field, muſt bee concluded to want faith: yea and every mans death, muſt be a judgement for ſome particular finne, and want of faith in a temporall promiſe (aſwell as in the caſe of the Plague) which by his opinion muſt needs follow, and ſo none at all ſhall be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid to die in faith, but through unbeleefe, at leaſt in reſpect of temporall promiſes.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe according to this interpretation, the plague muſt be the puniſhment only of wicked men, for ſo are the words: <hi>with thine eyes ſhalt thou behold the reward of the wicked</hi> verſe 8. and ſo all that die of the Plague muſt be condemned for wicked men, even upon that evidence, that they die of that diſeaſe; which were a very wicked opinion to hold: <hi>Hezekiah</hi> was ſick, and might have died of the Plague, as he was told: <hi>Iſay</hi> 38.1. <hi>David</hi> demanded con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them in his time: <hi>theſe ſheep, what have they done?</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.17. he accounted them not greater ſinners than others, becauſe they were ſo viſited; but more innocent (in reſpect of that particular) than himſelfe: many godly and faithfull people in all ages have been taken off with this vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation: yea (which is much to be obſerved, ſome in our owne times,<note place="margin">Note.</note> men of note that have held the opinion of this Temporary, have died of the ſame diſeaſe, for a warning to all to beware how they tempt the Lord with their folly, and this man in particular, who proclaimed before many, that if ever they heard,<note place="margin">The time and place afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</note> that he died of the plague, they ſhould report he wanted faith: to expound the <hi>Pſalme</hi> then according to the letter, we ſee how many unavoidable errours it will bring forth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> It may be demanded what then is the true ſenſe and meaning of the came?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:13575:28"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ſumme and ſubſtance of the <hi>Pſal.</hi> may be comprehended in this aſſertion following.</p>
            <p>That ſuch as the Lord will protect by his power,<note place="margin">The ſumme of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.</note> ſhall not need to dread any evill whatſoever, be it the ſnare of the hunter, the wiles of Satan, and his inſtruments; both of them, as fierce and fell, as Lyons, Dragons, and Aſpes: or the moſt noyſome diſeaſe, be it the plague or peſtilence, which deſtroyeth mightily,<note place="margin">See <hi>Calvin</hi> on the <hi>Pſal.</hi>
               </note> or yet the ſword and weapons of warre, though never ſo ſharp and deadly, nor any other miſchiefe from any other creature. But if it pleaſe him to leave any of his ſervants to ſuch an outward evill, to be taken away by any of thoſe means before mentioned, then it is in mercy, and diſpoſed of for their good, either to prove them, or to prevent greater evills, that are to come upon themſelves and others, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 34.28. or to chaſten them ſo here, that they may not be condemned for ever, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.32, which is not therfore done, becauſe the Lord doth faile in his power, providence, or truth towards his owne; but becauſe he ſeeth it beſt for them at ſuch a time, in ſuch a manner, by ſuch a means to be ſo viſited by him; None of the temporall promiſes being intended againſt, but for the works of mercy, to which they are all ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and not predominant; the fulfilling of them in their kind; being no certaine evidence of love, nor the contrary of hatred to any, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.1. upon which ground it may come to paſſe that any of the ſervants of God may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away (as many have beene) with the ſword, or with the peſtilence, and yet not through want of faith in the temporall promiſes, much leſſe becauſe they are wicked, and forſaken perſons.</p>
            <p>Which expoſition agreeth: Firſt,<note place="margin">See Treatiſe on the fourth petition.</note> with the nature of all temporall promiſes concerning health, wealth, ſtrength, long life, good ſucceſſe, and the like, that are varied accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the will of God: Secondly, the condition of all the faithfull in outward matters, of which it is teſtified by <hi>Salomon, that all things come alike unto all, and there is one event to him that feareth God, and to him that feareth him
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13575:29"/>not, Eccleſ.</hi> 9.2. confirmed by continuall experience: Thirdly, with the judgements of the learned in all times, and of expoſitors upon this <hi>Pſalme,</hi> heare one of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Although God do ſometimes permit the godly themſelves to be infected and die of the plague, or to periſh by other dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, yet that is nothing againſt this teſtimony and promiſe: becauſe the promiſes of temporall good things, have a ſilent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception annexed, unleſſe the Lord ſhall ſee it fit to doe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, for cauſes knowne to himſelfe.</hi> Piſcator.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The contrary, what is it but an uncouth and uncomfortable errour, ſavouring of much ignorance in the ſenſe of the Scriptures, putting conditionall promiſes for abſolute, and abuſing the faith of the ſervants of God, to their great diſcouragement.</p>
            <p>To all that feare God, then, would I direct this admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, to look there be no plague in their hearts,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.38.</note> no ſinne unrepented off, but to make their peace in heaven through Chriſt, to walk faithfully in the way of God, and to uſe all lawfull and good meanes for their preſervation: and then not to be ſervilly affraid of any creature, no not of the peſtilence it ſelfe, which either ſhall not touch them, or if it do, yet not in wrath for deſtruction, (as others) but to looſe the ſoule out of the priſon of the body, with more ſpeed (and it may be eaſe) than many other diſeaſes would have done; remembring that of the Apoſtle: <hi>That neither life, nor death, neither principalities, nor powers, neither things preſent, nor to come, nor any other creature ſhall be able to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate us from the love of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord,</hi> Rom. 8.38, 39.</p>
            <p>And for this peremptory dogmatizer, who ſends forth his immodeſt and ignorant dictates into all parts to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his own ſhame; if he were capable of admonition, I would adviſe him to do,<note place="margin">And of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and lies of <hi>Traske,</hi> if it were he.</note> as his betters have done before him; make certaine retractions of his errors, and falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, call in his exorbitant and unruly excurſions; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of his perſonall reproaches and ſlanders (againſt his owne knowledge and conſcience) eſpecially that blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:13575:29"/>imputation of diſtemper, on the holy prayer of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, unworthy of a Chriſtian: together with his foule handling of the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> in divers parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, as matters that will not only lie upon his name which already is little worth; but upon his conſcience which ſhould be pretious to him.</p>
            <p>And then before he print any more books, intermeddle any further in Controverſies, or undertake ſuch high points as the cenſure of all Churches, tranſcending his capacity; to labour to be better grounded in his Catechiſme, to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the Articles of Chriſtian Religion;<note place="margin">His ignorance is apparent in theſe things.</note> to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the difference betweene the Law, and the Goſpell; the nature of the new Covenant, what an abſolute, and a conditionall promiſe is; withall to labour for an humble heart, the feare of God, the ſpirit of truth, and the power of grace to governe his affections: and then he ſhall ſee, that which now he doth not, and be aſhamed of what he now glorieth in, bewailing thoſe monuments of ignorance and folly hee hath publiſhed to the world, which I heartily wiſh he may do, or that all, may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware what they receive for truth, from one, that hath ſo little in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is an honour for a man to ceaſe from ſtrife: but every foole will be medling,</hi> Prov. 20.3.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
